<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<program name='0compile'
	 author='Thomas Leonard'
	 feed='http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/0compile.xml'
	 git='http://repo.or.cz/w/0compile.git'
	 license='GNU Lesser General Public License'>

<p>
Normally, Zero Install will select a pre-built binary for your system. However, it can also be used to compile
a new binary from a source package. This is useful if:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>no binary is available for your platform;</li>
 <li>you wish to build using different library versions; or</li>
 <li>you wish to make changes to a program or library.</li>
</ul>

</program>

<p>
This tutorial shows how to use <b>0compile</b> for these purposes. It is
assumed that you have already installed <a href='injector.html'>the Zero
Install injector</a> (0launch) and know how to run programs using it. To
get <b>0compile</b> itself, use:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0alias 0compile http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/0compile.xml</b>
</pre>

<p>
Note: this page describes the command-line interface to <b>0compile</b>. There
is also a graphical interface, which is used when you click on the <b>Compile</b>
button in the injector. The graphical interface provides similar options, but is
slightly more limited. Here are
<a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/node/360'>some screenshots</a>.
</p>

<toc level='h2'/>

<h2>Creating the build environment</h2>

<p>
To get started, run <b>0compile setup</b> with the URL of the program you want
to build. In this example, we'll use <a
href='http://www.gnu.org/software/hello/'>GNU-Hello</a>, a simple program
written by the FSF to demonstrate use of the popular GNU build tools:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile setup http://0install.net/tests/GNU-Hello.xml GNU-Hello</b>
Created directory GNU-Hello
</pre>

<p>
<b>0compile</b> will run <b>0launch --source</b> to select a
suitable version of the source code and download it. It will also locate and
download any dependencies (e.g. build tools or header files) the source may
have, although the <b>GNU-Hello</b> example feed doesn't list any.  </p>

<p>
The final argument names a directory for the build environment. If omitted, it defaults
to the last component of the URI, without the ".xml" extension (so we could
have just left it off in this case). <b>0compile</b> will create this directory
in the current directory.
</p>

<p>
All further <b>0compile</b> commands are run from inside this new directory,
which is currently empty except for a <b>0compile-env.xml</b> file recording
the version of GNU-Hello selected. If you want to change the selected
version(s) later, do:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>cd GNU-Hello</b>
$ <b>0compile setup</b>
</pre>

<h2>Building</h2>

<p>
To compile the program, use the <b>build</b> command (from inside the <b>GNU-Hello</b> directory):
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile build</b>
TMPDIR=/tmp/0compile-T5GJBj
BUILDDIR=/home/me/GNU-Hello/build
DISTDIR=/home/me/GNU-Hello/gnu-hello-linux-x86_64-1.3
SRCDIR=/home/me/.cache/0install.net/implementations/...
cd /tmp/GNU-Hello/build
Executing: "$SRCDIR/configure" --prefix="$DISTDIR" &amp;&amp; make install
...
</pre>

<p>
Note: GNU-Hello does not use Zero Install to get the C compiler (<b>gcc</b>) or the standard library
header files (<b>libc-dev</b>), so you should install these yourself. They come with most distributions.
</p>

<p>
<b>0compile</b> starts by creating two sub-directories: <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64</b> for the
final result (the exact name will depend on your system) and <b>build</b> for
any temporary files. It then executes a command specified in the source feed,
which actually builds the software (using the standard GNU build system in this
case).
</p>

<p>
Note that the command installs to the
<b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64</b> directory rather than to the usual <b>/usr/local</b>. In fact, if you have
<a href='http://plash.beasts.org/'>plash</a> installed, the command is run in a
sandbox with very limited write permissions. [ update: Plash support is temporarily disabled by default while a few issues are worked out; set $USE_PLASH_0COMPILE to turn it on again ]
</p>

<p>
Assuming the build is successful, <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64</b> will contain the final result,
including a handy <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install/GNU-Hello.xml</b> local feed file, which you can use to
run the new binary:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0launch gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install/GNU-Hello.xml</b>
Hello, world!
</pre>

<p>
In fact, since <b>GNU-Hello</b> doesn't list any dependencies, we could have just run
the <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/bin/hello</b> binary directly in this case. For more complex programs,
the feed file will be useful. You can also pass it to <b>0launch
--feed</b> to register the new binary under the program's normal URI:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0launch -c http://0install.net/tests/GNU-Hello.xml</b>
Can't find all required implementations:
- &lt;Interface http://0install.net/tests/GNU-Hello.xml> -> None

$ <b>0launch --feed gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install/GNU-Hello.xml</b>
1) Add as feed for 'http://0install.net/tests/GNU-Hello.xml'

$ <b>0launch -c http://0install.net/tests/GNU-Hello.xml</b>
Hello, world!
</pre>

<p>
If everything worked, you can now delete the <b>build</b> directory to save
space. However, if you're planning to modify the source and rebuild (described
in the next section) then you'll want to leave it there, as it will make
rebuilding faster.
</p>

<p>
For future reference, there is also a <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install/build-environment.xml</b> file.
This is a selections file, as produced by <b>0launch --source --get-selections</b>, but with a few extra
details of the build added, including the hostname of the machine used for the
build, a timestamp and your username. This file is written before the build
starts, so the build process may add to it.
</p>

<h2>Modifying the source</h2>

<p>
By default, <b>0compile</b> keeps the source code in the (read-only) Zero Install cache, so if you
want to make changes, the first step is to make a copy of it:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile copy-src</b>
Copied as '/home/me/GNU-Hello/src'
</pre>

<p>
Edit the source as needed with the text editor of your choice. For example, we can change the
message (here we're using <a href='http://www.gnu.org/fun/jokes/ed.msg.html'>ed, the standard text editor</a>):
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>ed src/hello.c</b>
5207
<b>%s/Hello, world!/Goodbye, world!/
wq</b>
5209
</pre>

<p>Recompile with <b>0compile build</b> as before:</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile build</b>
$ <b>0launch gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install/GNU-Hello.xml</b>
Goodbye, world!
</pre>

<p>
If you compare the new <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install</b> directory with the old one, you'll discover a couple of differences:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>A new file is present, <b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64/0install/from-1.3.patch</b>, containing a diff between the original sources and
 your modified ones (to display this without rebuilding, use <b>0compile diff</b>).</li>
 <li>The version number in the local feed has <b>-1</b> appended, to indicate that this version has been modified.</li>
</ul>

<p>
These two features make it very easy to keep track of what you changed, which may well come in handy later! However, if
you are making larger changes to the code then you will want to use a proper version control system (such as
<a href='http://git.or.cz/'>GIT</a>).
</p>

<h2>Publishing the binary</h2>

<p>
To share our new binary with other people, we just need to archive up the
<b>gnu-hello-linux-x86_64</b> directory and upload it to an FTP or HTTP server somewhere.
Pass the URL of the remote directory to <b>0compile</b> and upload the
resulting binary (note: the version will be 1.3-1 if you modified the source):
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile publish http://mysite/downloads</b>
Now upload 'gnu-hello-linux-x86_64-1.3.tar.bz2' as:
http://mysite/downloads/gnu-hello-linux-x86_64-1.3.tar.bz2
$ <b>scp gnu-hello-linux-x86_64-1.3.tar.bz2 mysite:/var/www/downloads/</b>
</pre>

<p>
As well as the <b>.tar.bz2</b> file, you will also get a
<b>GNU-Hello-1.3.xml</b> file in the main <b>GNU-Hello</b> directory.
You can use this new XML file to download the archive and run the program:</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0launch GNU-Hello-1.3.xml</b>
</pre>

<p>
You can either ask the maintainer of the program to add the implementation in this file to the
master feed, or you can create your own feed (and ask them to add that).
See the <a href='0publish.html'>0publish page</a> for full details, but as a quick summary
you can create a new signed feed like this:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0publish .../GNU-Hello.xml \
  --xmlsign \
  --set-interface-uri=http://mysite/interfaces/GNU-Hello.xml \
  --local=GNU-Hello-1.3.xml</b>
</pre>

<p>
Then upload the signed <b>.../GNU-Hello.xml</b> file and the exported GPG key to your webserver.
</p>

<h2>Making source available</h2>
<p>
If you wish to make source code available for others to use (as described above) then you need to add source
implementations to the program's feed file. This is almost exactly the same as adding binaries, except that
you give <b>src</b> as the machine type to <b>0publish</b>:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0publish /var/www/interfaces/MyProg.xml \
  --add-version=5 \
  --archive-url=http://mysite/downloads/myprog-5-src.tar.bz2 \
  --set-released=today \
  --set-arch=*-src</b>
</pre>

<p>
There are also some extra attributes you can add to the <b>implementation</b> element:
</p>

<dl>
 <dt>compile:command</dt>
 <dd>This must be present. Its value is a shell command, executed inside the <b>build</b> directory. It must compile the source
 in <b>$SRCDIR</b>, putting the final result (ready for distribution) in <b>$DISTDIR</b>. If this command starts to get complicated,
 you should move it to a script (either inside the main source archive or in a separate dependency) and just set this attribute
 to the command to run the script.</dd>

 <dt>compile:binary-main</dt>
 <dd>This optional attribute gives the value of the <b>main</b> attribute on the binary feed that is created. If it is not given, then
 the binary created cannot be executed (e.g., it is a library).</dd>

 <dt>compile:dup-src</dt>
 <dd>Some programs insist on creating files in their source directory, which is
typically a read-only directory when using Zero Install. In this case, set
<b>compile:dup-src='true'</b> and 0compile will copy everything in $SRCDIR
into 'build' before building.</dd>

</dl>

<p>
The <b>compile</b> prefix must be bound to <b>0compile</b>'s namespace somewhere, e.g.:
</p>

<pre>xmlns:compile="http://zero-install.sourceforge.net/2006/namespaces/0compile"</pre>

<p>
Note: You can keep the source implementations in a separate file (<b>MyProg-src.xml</b>) and add a feed from
the main feed, e.g.:
</p>

<pre>
  &lt;feed src='http://mysite/interfaces/MyProg<b>-src</b>.xml' <b>arch='*-src'</b>/&gt;
</pre>

<p>
The <b>arch</b> attribute lets the injector know that it doesn't need to fetch this file unless
it's looking for source code.
</p>

<h2>Making library headers available (-dev packages)</h2>

<p>
See <a href='make-headers.html'>Make-headers</a> for information about publishing library source and -dev packages.
</p>

<h2>Adding run-time dependencies</h2>

<p>
By default, the feed created for the new binary doesn't have any dependencies. There are two ways to add them:
</p>

<ul>
<li>You can annotate any &lt;requires&gt; element in your source feed with the 'include-binary' attribute. This
causes the dependency to appear in the generated binary's feed, in addition to being made available at
compile-time. e.g.
<pre>
    &lt;requires <b>compile:include-binary='true'</b> interface="http://my/library"&gt;
      &lt;environment insert="lib" name="MY_LIBRARY_DIR" mode="replace"/&gt;
    &lt;/requires&gt;
</pre>
</li>
<li>
You can edit the feed XML file directly during the build (it's in the <b>$DISTDIR/0install</b> directory).
</li>
</ul>

<h2>Tips</h2>

<dl>
 <dt>Python distutils</dt>
 <dd><p>
 You should use the <b>--build-base</b> option to make distutils build to 0compile's build directory, not under the source code (which is read-only). Unfortunately, this option
 isn't available with the <b>install</b> command, so you have to do the build in two steps. A typical command is:
 </p>
 <pre>cd "$SRCDIR" &amp;&amp;
python setup.py build --build-base="$BUILDDIR/build" &amp;&amp;
cd "$BUILDDIR" &amp;&amp;
python "$SRCDIR"/setup.py install --home="$DISTDIR" --skip-build</pre>
 </dd>
</dl>

<h2>Further reading</h2>

<dl>
 <dt><a href='0compile-scons.html'>Example: SCons</a></dt>
 <dd>This example shows how to compile a simple "Hello world" program using
 the SCons build system. Both the source and SCons are fetched using Zero
 Install.</dd>
</dl>

</html>
