<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>Example: 0compile and SCons</h2>

<p>
<b>Hello-scons</b> is a simple "Hello world" program written in C. It is built using SCons.
</p>

<p>
Its purpose is to demonstrate the use of 0compile to fetch build dependencies;
you do not need to install SCons manually on your system in order to build it.
</p>

<p>
This example assumes that you have already read
<a href='0compile.html'>the main 0compile tutorial</a>.
</p>

<p>
You can try it out by using the <b>setup</b> command as usual:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile setup http://0install.net/tests/Hello-scons.xml Hello-scons</b>
</pre>

<p>
<b>0compile</b> will create a 'Hello-scons' directory for the build.
You will be prompted to choose the versions of Hello-scons and SCons.
</p>

<p>
To build, change into the new directory and use the build command:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>cd Hello-scons</b>
$ <b>0compile build</b>
</pre>

<p>
This creates a 'hello-scons-1.0' directory ready for use and/or distribution,
and a 'build' directory with some temporary files, such as 'hello.o'. This is
used only to speed up later rebuilds.
</p>

<p>
To run:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0launch hello-scons-1.0/0install/Hello-scons.xml</b>
Hello world!
</pre>

<p>
To see (or modify) a copy of the source:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0compile copy-src</b>
Copied as '/home/me/Hello-scons/src'
</pre>

<p>
The main issues with using SCons with 0compile are that:
</p>

<ul>
<li><p>SCons defaults to saving build files in the source directory. <b>0compile</b>
requires that the source directory is assumed to be read-only (and if
plash is installed, this is enforced). Therefore, you must set the build
and signature database directories to the build directory.</p></li>

<li><p>By default, SCons resets all environment variables. This means that
instead of compiling against the library versions you chose, it will
build against whatever happens to be the default on the system today.
This also breaks plash, which requires certain variables to be set.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>
The <b>src/SConstruct</b> file shows how to fix these problems.
</p>

<p>
For more information (including how to publish the binary using Zero Install),
see <a href='0compile.html'>the main 0compile tutorial</a>.
</p>


</html>
