<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html>

<div>
<h2>0install 2.0 - DRAFT release notes</h2>

<toc level='h3'/>

<h3>About 0install</h3>

<p>
Zero Install is a decentralised cross-platform software installation system
available under the LGPL. It allows software developers to publish programs
directly from their own web-sites, while supporting features familiar from
centralised distribution repositories such as shared libraries, automatic
updates and digital signatures. It is intended to complement, rather than
replace, the operating system's package management. 0install packages never
interfere with those provided by the distribution.
</p>

<p>
Zero Install is available from the official repositories of most Linux distributions
(including Debian, Fedora, Gentoo, Mint, OpenSUSE and Ubuntu), from MacPorts or as a
self-contained bundle on OS X, and there is a .NET Windows frontend. On other platforms,
it can be installed easily from source.
See the <a href='injector.html'>Downloads page</a> for details.
</p>

<p>
See <a href='why.html'>About 0install</a> for more information.
</p>

<h3>Overview of changes in 2.0</h3>

<p>
0install 2.0 brings many enhancements to the XML metadata syntax used to describe packages and their
dependencies, allowing a more precise specification of their requirements. Support for using distribution-provided
packages as dependencies was extended and now covers Arch Linux, Cygwin, Darwin, Debian, Fink, FreeBSD Ports, Gentoo, MacPorts, Mint, OpenSUSE, Red Hat, Slackware and Windows. The 0install software now supports <i>apps</i>, an easier way to manage 0install applications, improved diagnostics when no compatible versions can be selected, improved usability, and better support for use on headless servers.
</p>

<p>
<a href='http://www.ryppl.org/'>The Ryppl project</a> is using 0install as the package manager for a modular C++ build system, starting with a modularised C++ Boost library. This has driven many of the enhancements in 2.0, such as support compiling 0install packages on Windows. We hope that 0install will one day replace many of the language-specific packaging systems currently in use.
</p>

<h3>Extensions to the XML feed format</h3>

<p>The 2.0 feed format is 100% backwards compatible with the 1.0 format (all software distributed for 1.0 will also work with 2.0). The new features are:</p>

<dl>
  <dt>Optional dependencies</dt>
  <dd>We try to select the best available version of the dependency, but it's OK if nothing can be selected (this is useful if a dependency isn't available on all platforms):
  <pre>&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#dependencies'>requires</a> ... importance='optional'>...&lt;/requires></pre>
</dd>

<dt>OS-specific dependencies</dt>
<dd>For dependencies that are only needed on Windows, etc:
<pre>&lt;requires ... os='Windows'>...&lt;/requires></pre>
</dd>

<dt>Restrict-only dependencies</dt>
<dd>
These let you specify constraints/conflicts on the acceptable versions of another interface without requiring that interface to be selected at all:
<pre>&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#dependencies'>restricts</a> interface='...' version='...'></pre>
</dd>

<dt>Dependencies for native packages</dt>
<dd>These are useful when a distribution package is only for a particular major version of another interface:
<pre>
&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#package-implementation'>package-implementation</a> distributions="Debian" package="python3-gi">
  &lt;restricts interface="http://repo.roscidus.com/python/python">
    &lt;version not-before="3" before="4"/>
  &lt;/restricts>
&lt;/package-implementation>
</pre>
</dd>

<dt>Restrictions on distribution type</dt>
<dd>Some native packages only work with other packages from the same distribution. For example, MacPorts Python libraries only work with the MacPorts Python:
<pre>&lt;restricts interface='...' distribution='MacPorts'></pre>
The value can be any <a href='distribution-integration.html'>valid distribution name</a> (e.g. 'RPM'), or '0install' to force a
0install implementation, not a package implementation.
</dd>

<dt>More flexible version syntax</dt>
<dd>
The new 'version' attribute provides a shorter and more flexible way to specify the compatible versions:
<pre>&lt;requires interface='...' version='2.6..!3 | 3.2..'></pre>
This allows any version from 2.6 up to (but excluding) 3, or version 3.2 or later.
However, the previous syntax using &lt;version> should be used where possible, since it works with all versions of 0install.
</dd>

<dt>Executable bindings</dt>
<dd>Two new bindings make it easy to depend on executable commands (not just on libraries). This is necessary on Windows, since it doesn't support #! lines, but it is also useful on other platforms. For example, if a program requires the "make" command in $PATH:
<pre>
&lt;requires interface='http://repo.roscidus.com/devel/make'>
  &lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#executable'>executable-in-path</a> name='make'/>
&lt;/requires>
</pre>
Or, if it requires the make command in $MAKE:
<pre>
&lt;requires interface='http://repo.roscidus.com/devel/make'>
  &lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#executable'>executable-in-var</a> name='MAKE'/>
&lt;/requires>
</pre>
</dd>

<dt>Custom path separators in environment bindings</dt>

<dd>The path separator can now be specified in environment bindings (previously, it was either ":" or ";", depending on the platform):
<pre>&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#environment'>environment</a> name='OPTIONS' value='foo' separator=','></pre>
</dd>

<dt>Replaced interfaces</dt>
<dd>Obsolete interfaces can be flagged as such. Various tools will warn about the use of obsolete interfaces, and 0install knows that interfaces conflict with their replacements. For example, the "openjdk-6-jre" interface was replaced by the more general "openjdk-jre" (which covers versions 6 and 7):
<pre>&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#replaced-by'>replaced-by</a> interface="http://repo.roscidus.com/java/openjdk-jre"/></pre>
</dd>

<dt>Bindings inside &lt;command></dt>
<dd>This allows for bindings which are only needed when testing, etc.</dd>

<dt>New "POSIX" architecture</dt>
<dd>This matches everything except Windows.</dd>

<dt>New digest algorithm to avoid the "=" character</dt>
<dd>The new sha256new algorithm is the same as sha256, except that the digest is encoded with base 32 rather than base 16 (for shorter strings), and the separator is '_' rather than '=', since '=' causes problems for some programs (e.g. cmake) if it appears in pathnames.</dd>

<dt>Allow renaming files when unpacking</dt>
<dd><pre>
&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#recipe'>recipe</a>>
 &lt;archive href="..."/>
 &lt;rename source="run.sh" dest="start.sh"/>
&lt;/recipe>
</pre></dd>

<dt>Expand environment variables to multiple arguments</dt>
<dd>This is useful for variables which contain e.g. a list of options:
<pre>
&lt;<a href='interface-spec.html#commands'>for-each</a> item-from="EXTRA_OPTIONS" separator=" ">
  &lt;arg>-X&lt;/arg>
  &lt;arg>${item}&lt;/arg>
&lt;/for-each>
</pre>
This is needed to support SWT on OS X with Java 7.</dd>

<dt>Hide elements from certain versions of 0install</dt>
<dd>
To avoid breaking older versions of 0install when adding new features,
any element in a feed can be tagged with a version expression, and only those
versions will look at it. For example, to add a requirement element that would
confuse current versions of 0install, you might one day write:
<pre>&lt;requires <a href='interface-spec.html#if-0install-version'>if-0install-version</a>="2.7.." .../></pre>
</dd>
</dl>

<h3>Distribution support</h3>

<p>
As well as being able to download and manage 0install packages, 0install also allows programs
to depend on <a href='distribution-integration.html'>native packages</a> from the user's distribution. Enhancements here include:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Improved support for detecting native Java packages (on Arch, Debian, OpenSUSE, Fedora, OS X and Windows).</li>

<li>Support for detecting .NET Framework installations on Windows.</li>

<li>Support for new distributions: Arch, Cygwin, Darwin, Fink and MacPorts.</li>

</ul>


<h3>Changes to the 0install tool</h3>

<dl>

<dt>App support</dt>
<dd>
<a href='user-guide-apps.html'>Apps</a> are a new system to replace
0install 1.0's aliases. The main difference between apps and
aliases is that apps store their current selections (in
~/.config/0install.net/apps/NAME/selections.xml). This means that they
start faster, because the solver isn't needed. They also store historical
selections, making it easy to roll-back to a previous set of selected versions.
The commands are:
<pre>
0install add NAME URI
0install run NAME
0install update NAME
0install show NAME
0install whatchanged NAME
0install destroy NAME
</pre>
</dd>

<dt>Specifying versions</dt>
<dd>
The new <a href='interface-spec.html#constraints'>range syntax</a> can be used on the command line with the new
--version attribute, e.g.
<pre>
$ 0install run --version=2.11 \
  http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/ROX-Filer --version
ROX-Filer 2.11
</pre>
As "!" is often a shell special character, remember to quote it when
specifying ranges.

The new --version-for option allows you to constrain the version of
dependencies too, not just the root. e.g. to force the use of Python
2.6 with Edit:
<pre>
$ 0install select http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit \
    --version-for http://repo.roscidus.com/python/python '2.6..!2.7'
</pre>
<p>
When using "0install add" or "0install update" these restrictions are
saved for later. So you could, for example, make separate apps for
Edit with Python 2.6 and Python 2.7:
</p>
<pre>
$ 0install add edit-py26 http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit \
           --version-for http://repo.roscidus.com/python/python '2.6..!2.7'

$ 0install add edit-py27 http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit \
           --version-for http://repo.roscidus.com/python/python '2.7..!2.8'
</pre>
</dd>

<dt>Diagnostics</dt>
<dd>
A major new feature in 2.0 is the hugely improved <a href='injector-trouble.html'>diagnostics</a> when a
solve fails (or fails to select the expected version).
</dd>

<dt>Tab completion</dt>
<dd>There is now very complete support for <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/6627'>shell tab completion for the "0install" command</a>.</dd>

<dt>New --dry-run feature</dt>
<dd>This replaces the old broken one. Instead of
telling you the first URL it would have fetched, which isn't helpful,
it actually does the downloads and shows the changes that it would
have made to the system (saving things in the cache, trusting GPG
keys, creating short-cuts, etc), as an educational aid.
</dd>

<dt>Site-local packages</dt>

<dd>
This makes things easier for <a href='0compile.html'>0compile</a>: instead of putting builds in the cache
and registering them with the interface, 0compile can now just drop a build in
~/.local/share/0install.net/site-packages/URI/VERSION and 0install
will find it and add it automatically. The build can be removed by
simply deleting the directory.
</dd>

<dt>0install digest</dt>
<dd>This replaces "0store manifest", but has a saner syntax.
It can also be used directly on an archive.</dd>

<dt>0install man</dt>
<dd>This is similar to the old '0alias --manpage', but also copes with app
launchers. So, to make man(1) work with 0install launchers, do:
<pre>alias man="0install man --"</pre>
</dd>

<dt>0install update</dt>
<dd>
This now notifies the user if there is a newer unselected version, and
suggests turning on help_with_testing if that might help.
</dd>

<dt>Mirroring of archives</dt>
<dd>0install 1.0 can use a <a href='0mirror.html'>mirror service</a> as a
fallback to get the XML feeds; 0install 2.0 can also use the mirror
to get missing archives.
Note however that our default public mirror server does not actually mirror any
archives by default.
</dd>

<dt>Better headless use</dt>
<dd>
We used to assume that a GUI was available whenever $DISPLAY was set. However,
there could be other reasons why the GUI can't be used, such as missing Python
modules, which we now cope with. There are new split <a href='install-linux.html#debian'>Debian packages</a> for
headless servers, to avoid pulling in any GUI dependencies.
</dd>

<dt>Translations</dt>

<dd>There's a new German translation, and a <a href='https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/0install/'>Transifex project</a> to support new translations.</dd>

</dl>

<h3>Internals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Internally, 0install can now run with Python 2 or 3, with PyGTK or PyGObject, and with GTK 2 or GTK 3.</li>

<li>We batch up queries to PackageKit for better performance.</li>

<li>The GUI no longer slows to a crawl when showing download progress for a package with hundreds of dependencies.</li>

<li>We use threads, not processes, for downloads. This is slightly faster and
uses less memory. We also now limit the number of concurrent downloads from a
single site, as opening a large number of simultaneous connections causes
problems for some networks and servers.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>Updates to related tools</h3>

<dl>
  <dt>0compile</dt>
  <dd><a href='0compile.html'>0compile</a> now works on Windows, not just POSIX systems. It gained support for &lt;command name='compile'> to give the compile command, allowing the use of &lt;runner>. It also now allows you to provide a template for the binary's XML.</dd>

  <dt>0downstream</dt>
  <dd>The new <a href="https://github.com/gfxmonk/0downstream">0downstream</a> tool makes it easy to generate feeds and keep them up to date based on an existing upstream project.</dd>

  <dt>0env</dt>
  <dd>The new <a href="http://gfxmonk.net/dist/0install/0env.xml">0env</a> tool makes it easy to step into a shell session with a particular library available.</dd>

  <dt>0install for Windows</dt>
  <dd>The <a href='http://0install.de/'>Windows port</a> has also been very active; see the separate <a href='http://0install.de/news/?lang=en'>Windows version news page</a> for details.</dd>

  <dt>Packaging guide</dt>
  <dd>The <a href='injector-packagers.html'>Packaging guide</a> has been improved and a set of <a href='templates.html'>template projects</a> have been created to help developers learn to use 0install.</dd>
</dl>

</div>

</html>
