<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html lang="en">

<program name='0publish'
	 author='Thomas Leonard'
	 feed='http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/0publish'
	 git='http://repo.or.cz/w/0publish.git'
	 license='GNU Lesser General Public License'>

<p>
Making a new release of your software can be time consuming and error-prone, so you'll probably want to script
as much as possible of it. The <b>0publish</b> command provides a set of useful transformations
for feed files which you can integrate into your release scripts.
</p>

</program>

<p>
If you're looking for a graphical environment instead, see <b>0publish-gui</b> in <a
href='injector-packagers.html'>the packaging guide</a>.
</p>

<p>
Note: <a href='0release.html'>0release</a> provides a more complete solution
for managing releases (0release uses 0publish internally, but also handles many
other aspects of making releases for you).
</p>

<toc level='h2'/>

<h2>General operation</h2>

<p>
<b>0publish</b> edits feed files in place. It loads the file, transforms it in some way (such as
setting the release date, or adding a new implementation) and then writes it back out again. If the input
file was signed, it will resign it when saving with the same key by default. You can also use it to add a
signature, or to change the signing key.
</p>

<p>You can create an alias for <b>0publish</b> in the usual way, to save typing:</p>
<pre>
$ <b>0alias 0publish http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/0publish</b>
</pre>

<p>
In build scripts, you would use the full URI or create a local function
so that users don't need to run 0alias first in order to build your
program (assuming you use <b>0publish</b> as part of the build process).
</p>

<p>
The <a href='package-scons.html'>SCons packaging tutorial</a> shows many examples
of using <b>0publish</b>.
</p>

<h2>0publish reference</h2>

<b>Usage: 0publish [options] feed.xml</b>

<h3>Options</h3>

<dl>
  <dt>-h, --help</dt><dd>Show help message and exit.</dd>
  <dt>--add-types</dt><dd>add missing MIME-type attributes.</dd>
  <dt>--add-version=VERSION</dt><dd>Add a new implementation (use with <b>--archive-url</b>, etc).</dd>
  <dt>--archive-url=URL, --archive-file=FILE, --archive-extract=DIR</dt>
  <dd>Change a local implementation to one with a digest and an archive.
  See the <a href='package-scons.html'>SCons tutorial</a> for an example.</dd>
  <dt>-c, --create</dt><dd>Create a new feed file (if non-existent) without prompting.</dd>
  <dt>-d ALG, --add-digest=ALG</dt><dd>Add extra digests using the given algorithm.</dd>
  <dt>-e, --edit</dt><dd>Edit with $EDITOR. This is useful if the file is signed, since
  it removes the signature at the start and resigns at the end. It also checks that the
  new feed is valid before overwriting the old copy.</dd>
  <dt>-g, --gpgsign</dt><dd>Add a GPG signature block. Deprecated; use --xmlsign instead.</dd>
  <dt>-kKEY, --key=KEY</dt><dd>Key to use for signing (if you have more than one, or if you want to
  resign with a different key).</dd>
  <dt>-lLOCAL, --local=LOCAL</dt><dd>Create or update a feed from another feed.</dd>
  <dt>--manifest-algorithm=ALG</dt><dd>Select the algorithm to use for manifest digests.</dd>
  <dt>--set-id=DIGEST</dt><dd>Set the implementation ID.
  Note: it's usually easier to use the <b>--archive-*</b> options, since they calculate the digest for you.</dd>
  <dt>--set-main=EXEC</dt><dd>Set the main executable.</dd>
  <dt>--set-arch=ARCH</dt><dd>Set the architecture.</dd>
  <dt>--set-released=DATE</dt><dd>Set the release date.
  Typically used as <b>0publish --set-released `date +%F` feed.xml</b>, which sets today's date.</dd>
  <dt>--set-stability=STABILITY</dt><dd>Set the stability rating.</dd>
  <dt>--set-version=VERSION</dt><dd>Set the version number (used when making a release from CVS).</dd>
  <dt>-s, --stable</dt><dd>Mark the current testing version as stable.</dd>
  <dt>--select-version=VERSION</dt><dd>Select version to use in --set-* commands.</dd>
  <dt>-x, --xmlsign</dt><dd>Add an XML signature block. All remote feeds must be signed.</dd>
  <dt>-u, --unsign</dt><dd>Remove any signature.</dd>
  <dt>-v, --verbose</dt><dd>More verbose output (for debugging).</dd>
  <dt>-V, --version</dt><dd>Display version information.</dd>
</dl>

<h2>FAQ</h2>

<h3>gpg: signing failed: secret key not available</h3>

<p>
  By default, 0publish tries to sign the new version of the feed using the same key that
  signed the old version. You will get this error if you don't have this key (e.g. because
  someone else signed the old version). In that case, use <b>-k</b> to specify they key
  you want to use instead.
</p>

</html>
