<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='resources/catalog.xsl'?>
<c:catalog xmlns="http://zero-install.sourceforge.net/2004/injector/interface" xmlns:c="http://0install.de/schema/injector/catalog"><interface uri="http://0install.net/2013/interfaces/0install-windows-support.xml"><name>0install-windows-support</name><summary>support for 0install on Windows</summary><homepage>http://0install.net/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2009/interfaces/pkg2zero.xml"><name>pkg2zero</name><summary>create Zero Install feeds from Debian and RPM packages</summary><description>
Zero Install is a decentralised installation system. Meta-data about each
package is published in a &quot;feed&quot; file. The Zero Install client reads these feeds
files and downloads and runs the programs. The feed files can be created
manually (e.g. using 0publish or 0publish-gui). However, Debian and RPM packages already
contain much of the required information. This program extracts the information
in an existing package and uses it to generate the feed.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/pkg2zero.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2009/interfaces/pkg2zero-testdata.xml"><name>pkg2zero-testdata</name><summary>data for unit-tests</summary><description>
    These files are needed to run the unit-tests for pkg2zero. As they are
    quite large, they have their own package.
  </description><homepage>http://0install.net/pkg2zero.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2009/3rd-party/clutter.xml"><name>clutter</name><summary>creating fast, visually rich and animated graphical user interfaces</summary><description>
Clutter is an open source software library for creating fast, visually rich and
animated graphical user interfaces.

Clutter uses OpenGL (and optionally OpenGL ES for use on Mobile and embedded
platforms) for rendering but with an API which hides the underlying GL
complexity from the developer. The Clutter API is intended to be easy to use,
efficient and flexible.</description><homepage>http://www.clutter-project.org/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2009/3rd-party/python2.6-clutter.xml"><name>python-clutter</name><summary>Python bindings for the clutter library</summary><description>
Clutter is an open source software library for creating fast, visually rich and
animated graphical user interfaces.

Clutter uses OpenGL (and optionally OpenGL ES for use on Mobile and embedded
platforms) for rendering but with an API which hides the underlying GL
complexity from the developer. The Clutter API is intended to be easy to use,
efficient and flexible.</description><homepage>http://www.clutter-project.org/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2009/3rd-party/clutter-gtk.xml"><name>clutter-gtk</name><summary>embed clutter in GTK</summary><description>
Clutter is an open source software library for creating fast, visually rich and
animated graphical user interfaces.

Clutter uses OpenGL (and optionally OpenGL ES for use on Mobile and embedded
platforms) for rendering but with an API which hides the underlying GL
complexity from the developer. The Clutter API is intended to be easy to use,
efficient and flexible.

This package allows embedding a Clutter stage inside a GTK window.</description><homepage>http://www.clutter-project.org/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2009/3rd-party/python2.5-clutter.xml"><name>python-clutter</name><summary>Python bindings for the clutter library</summary><description>
Clutter is an open source software library for creating fast, visually rich and
animated graphical user interfaces.

Clutter uses OpenGL (and optionally OpenGL ES for use on Mobile and embedded
platforms) for rendering but with an API which hides the underlying GL
complexity from the developer. The Clutter API is intended to be easy to use,
efficient and flexible.</description><homepage>http://www.clutter-project.org/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tools/0repo.xml"><name>0repo</name><summary>manage a repository of 0install feeds</summary><description>
    0repo allows a group of developers to publish a set of feeds. It can be
    used by a single developer, generating a set of static files to publish on
    a web-server, or as a service which accepts signed updates from a group
    of developers.
  </description><homepage>http://0install.net/0repo.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tools/0export.xml"><name>0export</name><summary>create self-installing bundles for distribution on CD</summary><description>
It is sometimes useful to bundle a program and its libraries together
on a CD (for example) so that it can be used on machines without a network
connection, or where the network is very slow. It is also useful for archival
purposes, in case the original web-sites supplying required libraries become
unavailable.

0export takes the URI of a program and creates a &quot;setup.sh&quot; file; a self-
extracting archive containing everything needed to run the program. This file
can be executed on a machine without a network connection to install or run the
program.

Unlike the bundles created by the related zero2bundle program, programs
installed using setup.sh are added to the Zero Install cache and are therefore
still shared between users, and will get updates over the web where possible.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/0export.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tools/0template.xml"><name>0template</name><summary>utility to make creating feeds easier</summary><description>
    0template takes a template XML file (e.g. with place-holders for the version),
    fills in the place-holders, and then fills in everything else it can. For example,
    it will download the archive, fill in the size, calculate the digests, etc.
  </description><homepage>http://0install.net/0template.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2010/interfaces/xzdec.xml"><name>xzdec</name><summary>XZ Decompressor</summary><description>
xzdec is a liblzma-based decompression-only tool for .xz files.</description><homepage>http://tukaani.org/xz/</homepage><category>Utility</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/libxml2-dev.xml"><name>libxml2-dev</name><summary>headers for libxml2</summary><description>
Libxml2 is the XML C parser and toolkit developed for the Gnome project (but
usable outside of the Gnome platform), it is free software available under the
MIT License. XML itself is a metalanguage to design markup languages, i.e. text
language where semantic and structure are added to the content using extra
&quot;markup&quot; information enclosed between angle brackets. HTML is the most well-
known markup language. Though the library is written in C a variety of language
bindings make it available in other environments.</description><homepage>http://xmlsoft.org/</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/libglade-dev.xml"><name>libglade-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling Glade applications</summary><description>
These are the Glade header files. They are required when compiling applications
that use the Glade library.</description><homepage>http://glade.gnome.org</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/0share.xml"><name>0share</name><summary>peer-to-peer sharing of Zero Install packages</summary><description>
Zero Install is a decentralised installation system. Meta-data about each
package is published in a &quot;feed&quot; file.

Before downloading a package over the internet, 0launch can check to see if any
nearby machines have a copy, and get it from them instead if so. This will
normally be much faster. The secure hash from the feed is used to check that the
software hasn't been modified.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/0share.html</homepage><category>Network</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/lzmadec.xml"><name>lzmadec</name><summary>small and fast LZMA decoder</summary><description>
lzmadec is a small and fast decoder for LZMA compressed files. It is intended to
work as a drop-in replacement for lzma in situations where available disk space
is limited, only decoder is needed and the data can be decompressed from the
standard input to the standard output. This has been achieved by simply ignoring
all command line arguments except --help.</description><homepage>http://tukaani.org/lzma/</homepage><category>Utility</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/deb2zero.xml"><name>deb2zero</name><summary>create Zero Install feeds from Debian packages</summary><description>
Zero Install is a decentralised installation system. Meta-data about each
package is published in a &quot;feed&quot; file. The Zero Install client reads these feeds
files and downloads and runs the programs. The feed files can be created
manually (e.g. using 0publish or 0publish-gui). However, Debian packages already
contain much of the required information. This program extracts the information
in an existing Debian package and uses it to generate the feed.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/deb2zero.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/ZeroInstall-GUI.xml"><name>ZeroInstall-GUI</name><summary>graphical interface for the Zero Install injector</summary><description>
The Zero Install GUI displays a window showing which versions of various
components will be used when running a program, and allows you to alter various
policy settings to affect the selection process. You can use this to mark
particular versions of libraries as preferred, bugggy, etc.

This program is run automatically by the '0launch' command. If you want to add
an installer to your desktop menus, you want something like Zero2Desktop
instead.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/injector.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/interfaces/0test.xml"><name>0test</name><summary>test Zero Install programs</summary><description>
Use 0test to run the unit tests for a Zero Install program. You can use this to
test released versions or developer snapshots. You can give a selection of
versions to test, and you can test against different versions of dependencies to
create a matrix of test results.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/0test.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libmng1.xml"><name>libmng1</name><summary>Multiple-image Network Graphics library</summary><description>The libmng library supports decoding, displaying, encoding, and various
other manipulations of the Multiple-image Network Graphics (MNG) format
image files. It uses the zlib compression library, and optionally the
JPEG library by the Independent JPEG Group (IJG) and/or
lcms (little cms), a color-management library by Marti Maria Saguar.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libsdl-image1.2.xml"><name>libsdl-image1.2</name><summary>image loading library for Simple DirectMedia Layer 1.2</summary><description>This is a simple library to load images of various formats as SDL surfaces.
This library currently supports BMP, PPM, PCX, GIF, JPEG, PNG, TIFF, and XPM
formats.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libvorbis0a.xml"><name>libvorbis0a</name><summary>The Vorbis General Audio Compression Codec</summary><description>Ogg Vorbis is a fully open, non-proprietary, patent-and-royalty-free,
general-purpose compressed audio format for audio and music at fixed
and variable bitrates from 16 to 128 kbps/channel.

The Vorbis library is the primary Ogg Vorbis library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/groundhog.xml"><name>groundhog</name><summary>A simple logic game</summary><description>The purpose of this game is to put balls in pockets of the same color
by manipulating a maze of tubes.

Homepage: http://home-2.consunet.nl/~cb007736/groundhog.html</description><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libtasn1-3.xml"><name>libtasn1-3</name><summary>Manage ASN.1 structures (runtime)</summary><description>Manage ASN1 (Abstract Syntax Notation One) structures.
The main features of this library are:
  * on-line ASN1 structure management that doesn't require any C code
    file generation.
  * off-line ASN1 structure management with C code file generation
    containing an array.
  * DER (Distinguish Encoding Rules) encoding
  * no limits for INTEGER and ENUMERATED values

This package contains runtime libraries.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libcurl3-gnutls.xml"><name>libcurl3-gnutls</name><summary>Multi-protocol file transfer library</summary><description>libcurl is designed to be a solid, usable, reliable and portable
multi-protocol file transfer library.

SSL support is provided by GnuTLS.
To enable LDAP support package libldap2-dev is required.

This is the shared version of libcurl.

 Homepage: http://curl.haxx.se</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libvorbisfile3.xml"><name>libvorbisfile3</name><summary>The Vorbis General Audio Compression Codec</summary><description>Ogg Vorbis is a fully open, non-proprietary, patent-and-royalty-free,
general-purpose compressed audio format for audio and music at fixed
and variable bitrates from 16 to 128 kbps/channel.

The Vorbisfile library provides a convenient high-level API for decoding
and basic manipulation of all Vorbis I audio streams.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/gnome-inform7.xml"><name>gnome-inform7</name><summary>GNOME port of the Inform 7 IDE</summary><description>
GNOME Inform 7 is a GNOME port of the Inform 7 integrated development
environment for Inform 7. Inform 7 is a &quot;natural&quot; programming language for
writing interactive fiction (also known as text adventures.)</description><category>Development</category><homepage>http://sourceforge.net/projects/gnome-inform7</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/libsdl-mixer1.2.xml"><name>libsdl-mixer1.2</name><summary>mixer library for Simple DirectMedia Layer 1.2</summary><description>SDL Mixer is a sample multi-channel audio mixer library. It supports 4
channels of 16 bit stereo audio, plus a single channel of music, mixed by
the popular MikMod MOD, Timidity MIDI, and SMPEG MP3 libraries.

URL: http://www.libsdl.org/projects/SDL_mixer/</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/3rd-party/git.xml"><name>git-core</name><summary>fast, scalable, distributed revision control system</summary><description>Git is popular version control system designed to handle very large
projects with speed and efficiency; it is used mainly for various open
source projects, most notably the Linux kernel.

Git falls in the category of distributed source code management tools.
Every Git working directory is a full-fledged repository with full
revision tracking capabilities, not dependent on network access or a
central server.

This package provides the git main components with minimal dependencies.
Additional functionality, e.g. a graphical user interface and revision
tree visualizer, tools for interoperating with other VCS's, or a web
interface, is provided as separate git* packages.</description><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2008/linux-ppc/GLib-dev.xml"><name>GLib-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling GLib applications</summary><description>These are the GLib header files. They are required when compiling applications
that use the GLib library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tests/ebox-chat.xml"><name>ebox-chat</name><summary>sandboxed chat program</summary><description>
    EBox-Chat is a demonstration chat client. It allows secure two-way text-based communication with another instance of itself.
    It is designed to be installed using the ebox demonstration sandboxing system.
  </description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tests/ebox.xml"><name>ebox</name><summary>instance manager for E programs</summary><description>
ebox installs instances of E programs. Each program runs with access, by
default, only to its own instance directory. The code is separate; managed by
Zero Install.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tests/ebox-edit.xml"><name>edit</name><summary>E text editor</summary><description>
    This is a very simple proof-of-concept text editor that can be confined using the EBox sandbox system.
  </description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/tests/ebox-help.xml"><name>ebox-help</name><summary>EBox help viewer</summary><description>
    This library can be used by programs to display simple help text. It is part of the EBox sandbox proof-of-concept examples.
  </description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/FeedLint.xml"><name>FeedLint</name><summary>check your Zero Install feeds</summary><description>
FeedLint is a tool for Zero Install feed authors. It checks that your Zero
Install feed can be downloaded, that it is valid and that all the links in it
still work.

Run this on all your feeds from time-to-time to make sure they still work.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/feedlint.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/Zero2Desktop.xml"><name>Zero2Desktop</name><summary>add Zero Install programs to your Applications menu</summary><description>
Zero Install provides a way to download and run applications using a full URI to
identify them. To make applications easier to run you'll want to create a short-
cut in your desktop environment.

This program creates a freedesktop.org &quot;.desktop&quot; file, which causes the program
to appear in the GNOME or KDE Applications menus.</description><category>Utility</category><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/Zero2Desktop.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/Make-headers.xml"><name>Make-headers</name><summary>creates -dev packages</summary><description>
Given a standard autoconf source package (in $SRCDIR), this script builds it
(configure --prefix=$DISTDIR &amp;&amp; make install) and then removes files which
shouldn't be in a -dev package (.so and .la files, etc).

It also edits any pkg-config .pc files to use a relative path for the prefix.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/make-headers.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/0publish-gui.xml"><name>0publish-gui</name><summary>GTK editor for Zero Install feeds</summary><description>
Publishing a program using Zero Install requires you to create an XML file
listing the available versions, where to get them, and what other software they
depend on.

This program provides a simple graphical interface for creating and editing
these feeds.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/injector-packagers.html</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/0publish-gui.png" type="image/png"/><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/ZeroInstall-GUI.xml"><name>ZeroInstall-GUI</name><summary>graphical interface for the Zero Install injector</summary><description>
The Zero Install GUI displays a window showing which versions of various
components will be used when running a program, and allows you to alter various
policy settings to affect the selection process. You can use this to mark
particular versions of libraries as preferred, bugggy, etc.

This program is run automatically by the '0launch' command. If you want to add
an installer to your desktop menus, you want something like Zero2Desktop
instead.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/injector.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/ZeroInstall.xml"><name>0install</name><summary>decentralised installation system</summary><description>
Zero Install is a decentralised cross-platform software installation
system available under the LGPL. It allows software developers to publish
programs directly from their own web-sites, while supporting features familiar
from centralised distribution repositories such as shared libraries, automatic
updates and digital signatures. It is intended to complement, rather than
replace, the operating system's package management. 0install packages never
interfere with those provided by the distribution.
  </description><homepage>http://0install.net/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/ZeroInstall.png" type="image/png"/><category>System</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/interfaces/0release.xml"><name>0release</name><summary>manage new releases with Zero Install</summary><description>
If you have a local feed in the development version of your program, 0release
can help you to create new releases easily.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/0release.xml</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libssl0.9.8.xml"><name>libssl0.9.8</name><summary>SSL shared libraries</summary><description>
libssl and libcrypto shared libraries needed by programs like apache-ssl,
telnet-ssl and openssh.

It is part of the OpenSSL implementation of SSL.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libdb4.6.xml"><name>libdb4.6</name><summary>Berkeley v4.6 Database Libraries [runtime]</summary><description>This is the runtime package for programs that use the v4.6 Berkeley
database library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libaudio2.xml"><name>libaudio2</name><summary>the Network Audio System (NAS)</summary><description>
The Network Audio System was developed by NCD for playing, recording, and
manipulating audio data over a network. Like the X Window System, it uses the
client/server model to separate applications from the specific drivers that
control audio input and output devices.

This package contains the nas library (libaudio), needed for both remote and
local output.</description><homepage>http://radscan.com/nas.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/XdgUtils.xml"><name>XdgUtils</name><summary>cross-desktop integration tools</summary><description>
Xdg-utils is a set of command line tools that assist applications with a variety
of desktop integration tasks. About half of the tools focus on tasks commonly
required during the installation of a desktop application and the other half
focuses on integration with the desktop environment while the application is
running. Even if the desktop components of your application are limited to an
installer, configuration or management tool, Xdg-utils provides you with an easy
way to enhance the usage experience of your customers by improving the
integration of these components in the user's environment. Best of all, Xdg-
utils is provided as open source and free of charge.</description><homepage>http://portland.freedesktop.org</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libpq5.xml"><name>libpq5</name><summary>PostgreSQL C client library</summary><description>libpq is a C library that enables user programs to communicate with
the PostgreSQL database server. The server can be on another machine
and accessed through TCP/IP. This version of libpq is compatible
with servers from PostgreSQL 8.2 or later.

This package contains the run-time library, needed by packages using
libpq.

PostgreSQL is an object-relational SQL database management system.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libaprutil1.xml"><name>libaprutil1</name><summary>the Apache Portable Runtime Utility Library</summary><description>
APR is Apache's Portable Runtime Library, designed to be a support library that
provides a predictable and consistent interface to underlying platform-specific
implementations.

APR Util is a utilities library implemented on top of apr, providing database
access, xml parsing, and other useful functionality.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/APBuild.xml"><name>APBuild</name><summary>a suite of portability tools for developers</summary><description>
In the process of writing autopackage, we've also produced several standalone
tools, the apbuild programs, that are designed to help Linux developers write
better software that runs on a wider variety of distributions. They are
independent of autopackage itself: you can use them even if you don't provide
your software using the rest of our software.</description><homepage>http://autopackage.org/aptools.html</homepage><category>Development</category><icon href="http://autopackage.org/gnome-devel.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libgnutls26.xml"><name>libgnutls26</name><summary>the GNU TLS library - runtime library</summary><description>gnutls is a portable library which implements the Transport Layer
Security (TLS) 1.0 and Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) 3.0 protocols.

Currently gnutls implements:
 - the TLS 1.0 and SSL 3.0 protocols, without any US-export
   controlled algorithms
 - X509 Public Key Infrastructure (with several limitations).
 - SRP for TLS authentication.
 - TLS Extension mechanism

This package contains the runtime libraries.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libcomerr2.xml"><name>libcomerr2</name><summary>common error description library</summary><description>libcomerr is an attempt to present a common error-handling mechanism to
manipulate the most common form of error code in a fashion that does not
have the problems identified with mechanisms commonly in use.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libenchant1.xml"><name>libenchant1</name><summary>a wrapper library for various spell checker engines</summary><description>
Enchant is a generic spell checking library which uses existing spell checker
engines such as ispell, aspell and myspell as its backends.

Enchant steps in to provide uniformity and conformity on top of these libraries,
and implement certain features that may be lacking in any individual provider
library.</description><homepage>http://www.abisource.com/projects/enchant/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/Subversion.xml"><name>Subversion</name><summary>advanced version control system</summary><description>
Subversion, also known as svn, is a version control system much like the
Concurrent Versions System (CVS). Version control systems allow many individuals
(who may be distributed geographically) to collaborate on a set of files
(typically source code). Subversion has all the major features of CVS, plus
certain new features that CVS users often wish they had.

This package includes the Subversion client (svn), tools to create a Subversion
repository (svnadmin) and to make a repository available over a network
(svnserve).</description><homepage>http://subversion.tigris.org</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libgucharmap4.xml"><name>libgucharmap4</name><summary>unicode browser widget library</summary><description>
The libgucharmap library contains a Unicode browser widget; it is most
prominently used by the &quot;gucharmap&quot; program.

This package contains the shared library.</description><homepage>http://gucharmap.sourceforge.net/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libneon27-gnutls.xml"><name>libneon27-gnutls</name><summary>An HTTP and WebDAV client library (GnuTLS enabled)</summary><description>neon is an HTTP and WebDAV client library, with a C language API.

WARNING: THE NEON API IS NOT YET STABLE.

Provides lower-level interfaces to directly implement new HTTP
methods, and higher-level interfaces so that you don't have to
worry about the lower-level stuff.

Current features:
  * High-level interface to HTTP and WebDAV methods (PUT, GET, HEAD, etc.)
  * Low-level interface to HTTP request handling, to allow implementing
    new methods easily.
  * persistent connections
  * RFC2617 basic and digest authentication (including auth-int, md5-sess)
  * Proxy support (including basic/digest authentication)
  * SSL/TLS support using GnuTLS (including client certificate and thread
    safety support)
  * Generic WebDAV 207 XML response handling mechanism
  * XML parsing using the expat or libxml parsers
  * Easy generation of error messages from 207 error responses
  * WebDAV resource manipulation: MOVE, COPY, DELETE, MKCOL.
  * WebDAV metadata support: set and remove properties, query any set ofi
    properties (PROPPATCH/PROPFIND).
  * autoconf macros supplied for easily embedding neon directly inside an
    application source tree.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/UserModeLinux.xml"><name>UserModeLinux</name><summary>run Linux inside itself</summary><description>
User-Mode Linux is a safe, secure way of running Linux versions and Linux
processes. Run buggy software, experiment with new Linux kernels or
distributions, and poke around in the internals of Linux, all without risking
your main Linux setup.

User-Mode Linux gives you a virtual machine that may have more hardware and
software virtual resources than your actual, physical computer. Disk storage for
the virtual machine is entirely contained inside a single file on your physical
machine. You can assign your virtual machine only the hardware access you want
it to have. With properly limited access, nothing you do on the virtual machine
can change or damage your real computer, or its software.</description><category>System</category><homepage>http://user-mode-linux.sourceforge.net</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/UserModeLinux.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libsvn1.xml"><name>libsvn1</name><summary>shared libraries used by Subversion</summary><description>
This package includes shared libraries to manipulate Subversion (svn)
repositories and working copies.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/Mutt.xml"><name>Mutt</name><summary>text-based mail client</summary><description>
Mutt is a sophisticated text-based Mail User Agent.</description><homepage>http://www.mutt.org/</homepage><category>Network</category><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/Mutt.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libsqlite3-0.xml"><name>libsqlite3-0</name><summary>SQLite 3 shared library</summary><description>SQLite is a C library that implements an SQL database engine.
Programs that link with the SQLite library can have SQL database
access without running a separate RDBMS process.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/Tgif.xml"><name>Tgif</name><summary>interactive 2-D drawing tool</summary><description>
Tgif is an interactive drawing tool that allows the user to draw and manipulate
objects in the X Window System.</description><homepage>http://bourbon.usc.edu/tgif/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/Tgif.png" type="image/png"/><category>Graphics</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libkeyutils1.xml"><name>libkeyutils1</name><summary>Linux Key Management Utilities (library)</summary><description>Keyutils is a set of utilities for managing the key retention facility in the
kernel, which can be used by filesystems, block devices and more to gain and
retain the authorization and encryption keys required to perform secure
operations.

This package provides a wrapper library for the key management facility system
calls.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libserf-0-0.xml"><name>libserf-0-0</name><summary>high-performance asynchronous HTTP client library</summary><description>serf library is a C-based HTTP client library built upon the Apache
Portable Runtime (APR) library. It multiplexes connections, running the
read/write communication asynchronously. Memory copies and
transformations are kept to a minimum to provide high performance
operation.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libuuid1.xml"><name>libuuid1</name><summary>universally unique id library</summary><description>libuuid generates and parses 128-bit universally unique id's (UUID's).
See RFC 4122 for more information.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libpq4.xml"><name>libpq4</name><summary>PostgreSQL C client library</summary><description>
libpq is a C library that enables user programs to communicate with the
PostgreSQL database server. The server can be on another machine and accessed
through TCP/IP. This version of libpq is compatible with servers from PostgreSQL
7.3 to 8.1.

This package contains the run-time library, needed by packages using libpq.

PostgreSQL is an object-relational SQL database management system.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libmysqlclient15off.xml"><name>libmysqlclient15off</name><summary>MySQL database client library</summary><description>MySQL is a fast, stable and true multi-user, multi-threaded SQL database
server. SQL (Structured Query Language) is the most popular database query
language in the world. The main goals of MySQL are speed, robustness and
ease of use.

This package includes the client library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libdb4.4.xml"><name>libdb4.4</name><summary>Berkeley v4.4 Database Libraries</summary><description>
This is the runtime package for programs that use the v4.4 Berkeley database
library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/Django.xml"><name>Django</name><summary>the Web framework for perfectionists with deadlines</summary><description>
Django is a high-level Python Web framework that encourages rapid development
and clean, pragmatic design.

Developed and used over two years by a fast-moving online-news operation, Django
was designed to handle two challenges: the intensive deadlines of a newsroom and
the stringent requirements of the experienced Web developers who wrote it. It
lets you build high-performing, elegant Web applications quickly.</description><homepage>http://www.djangoproject.com/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libneon26.xml"><name>libneon26</name><summary>an HTTP and WebDAV client library</summary><description>
Neon is an HTTP and WebDAV client library, with a C language API.

WARNING: THE NEON API IS NOT YET STABLE.

Provides lower-level interfaces to directly implement new HTTP methods, and
higher-level interfaces so that you don't have to worry about the lower-level
stuff.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libkrb53.xml"><name>libkrb53</name><summary>MIT Kerberos runtime libraries</summary><description>
Kerberos is a system for authenticating users and services on a network.
Kerberos is a trusted third-party service. That means that there is a third
party (the kerberos server) that is trusted by all the entities on the network
(users and services, usually called &quot;principals&quot;).

This is the MIT reference implementation of Kerberos5.

This package contains the runtime libraries used by applications and Kerberos
clients.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/LyX.xml"><name>LyX</name><summary>WYSIWYM(ean) document processor</summary><description>
LyX is an advanced open source document processor running on many Unix and some
non-Unix platforms. It is called a &quot;document processor&quot;, because unlike standard
word processors, LyX encourages an approach to writing based on the structure of
your documents, not their appearance. LyX lets you concentrate on writing,
leaving details of visual layout to the software.

LyX automates formatting according to predefined rule sets, yielding consistency
throughout even the most complex documents. LyX produces high quality,
professional output -- using LaTeX, an open source, industrial strength
typesetting engine, in the background.

With LyX, short notes or letters are a snap. LyX really shines, though, when
composing complex documents like technical documentation, doctoral theses and
conference proceedings.</description><homepage>http://www.lyx.org</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/LyX.png" type="image/png"/><category>Office</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libgnutls13.xml"><name>libgnutls13</name><summary>the GNU TLS library</summary><description>
gnutls is a portable library which implements the Transport Layer Security (TLS)
1.0 and Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) 3.0 protocols.

Currently gnutls implements:

- the TLS 1.0 and SSL 3.0 protocols, without any US-export controlled algorithms

- X509 Public Key Infrastructure (with several limitations).

- SRP for TLS authentication.

- TLS Extension mechanism

This package contains the runtime libraries.</description><homepage>http://www.gnu.org/software/gnutls/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libqt-mt3.xml"><name>libqt-mt3</name><summary>Qt GUI Library (threaded runtime version)</summary><description>
This is the Trolltech Qt library, version 3. It's necessary for applications
that link against the libqt-mt.so.3, e.g. all KDE3 applications.</description><homepage>http://www.trolltech.com</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libldap-2.4-2.xml"><name>libldap-2.4-2</name><summary>OpenLDAP libraries</summary><description>These are the run-time libraries for the OpenLDAP (Lightweight Directory
Access Protocol) servers and clients.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libxml2.xml"><name>libxml2</name><summary>GNOME XML library</summary><description>XML is a metalanguage to let you design your own markup language.
A regular markup language defines a way to describe information in
a certain class of documents (eg HTML). XML lets you define your
own customized markup languages for many classes of document. It
can do this because it's written in SGML, the international standard
metalanguage for markup languages.

This package provides a library providing an extensive API to handle
such XML data files.

This feed is deprecated; use http://repo.roscidus.com/lib/xml2 instead.
</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libgcrypt11.xml"><name>libgcrypt11</name><summary>LGPL Crypto library - runtime library</summary><description>libgcrypt contains cryptographic functions. Many important free
ciphers, hash algorithms and public key signing algorithms have been
implemented:
arcfour, blowfish, cast5, DSA, DSA2, des, 3DES, elgamal, MD5, rijndael,
RMD160, RSA, SEED, SHA1, SHA-384, SHA-512, twofish, tiger.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libsasl2-2.xml"><name>libsasl2-2</name><summary>Cyrus SASL - authentication abstraction library</summary><description>This is the Cyrus SASL API implementation, version 2.1.

SASL is the Simple Authentication and Security Layer, a method for
adding authentication support to connection-based protocols. To use
SASL, a protocol includes a command for identifying and
authenticating a user to a server and for optionally negotiating
protection of subsequent protocol interactions. If its use is
negotiated, a security layer is inserted between the protocol and the
connection. See RFC 2222 for more information.

Any of: ANONYMOUS, CRAM-MD5, DIGEST-MD5, GSSAPI (MIT or Heimdal
Kerberos 5), NTLM, OTP, PLAIN, or LOGIN can be used. If you intend to
use this package on a server that provides SASL authentication, then
you must install some of the libsasl2-modules* packages.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/Blender.xml"><name>Blender</name><summary>a versatile 3D animation creation suite</summary><description>
Blender is a fully integrated 3D animation suite for use in animation, still
graphics, scientific and engineering visualization, and game content creation.

It includes tools for modeling, texturing (node based materials or uv mapped),
uv mapping, rigging and constraints, weight painting, particle systems,
simulation (fluids, physics, and soft body dynamics and an external crowd
simulator), rendering, node based compositing, and non linear video editing, as
well as an integrated game engine for real-time interactive 3D, and game
creation and playback with cross-platform compatibility.</description><homepage>http://www.blender.org</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/Blender.png" type="image/png"/><category>Video</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libldap2.xml"><name>libldap2</name><summary>run-time libraries for the OpenLDAP servers and clients</summary><description>
These are the run-time libraries for the OpenLDAP (Lightweight Directory Access
Protocol) servers and clients.</description><homepage>http://www.openldap.org/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libexpat1.xml"><name>libexpat1</name><summary>XML parsing C library</summary><description>
This package contains the runtime, shared library of expat, the C library for
parsing XML.</description><homepage>http://expat.sourceforge.net</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/mysql-common.xml"><name>mysql-common</name><summary>MySQL database common files</summary><description>MySQL is a fast, stable and true multi-user, multi-threaded SQL database
server. SQL (Structured Query Language) is the most popular database query
language in the world. The main goals of MySQL are speed, robustness and
ease of use.

This package includes files needed by all versions of the client library
(e.g. /etc/mysql/my.cnf).</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libgpg-error0.xml"><name>libgpg-error0</name><summary>library for common error values and messages in GnuPG components</summary><description>Library that defines common error values for all GnuPG
components. Among these are GPG, GPGSM, GPGME, GPG-Agent, libgcrypt,
pinentry, SmartCard Daemon and possibly more in the future.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2007/3rd-party/libapr1.xml"><name>libapr1</name><summary>the Apache Portable Runtime Library</summary><description>
APR is Apache's Portable Runtime Library, designed to be a support library that
provides a predictable and consistent interface to underlying platform-specific
implementations.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2012/interfaces/0install-runenv-cli.xml"><name>0install-runenv-cli</name><summary>0install .NET helper for Windows</summary><description>
    When 0install needs to add a new program to %PATH% on Windows, it uses this
    package to creates a .NET launcher application.
</description><homepage>http://0install.net/</homepage><category>System</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/GTK-dev"><name>GTK-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling GTK applications</summary><description>
These are the GTK header files. They are required when compiling applications
that use the GTK+ library.</description><icon href="http://0install.net/2006/icons/gtk-logo.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/0compile.xml"><name>0compile</name><summary>create a binary release from source code</summary><description>
0compile creates a binary from source code, either for your own use or ready for
publishing on the web through Zero Install. It can use Zero Install to download
any build dependencies (compilers, header files, build tools, etc).

This is useful if there is no binary for your platform, or if you wish to modify
the program in some way.

If plash is installed, it is used to sandbox the build so that it can't
accidentally modifiy any files outside of the build directory.

For a full tutorial, see 0compile's homepage.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/0compile.html</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/ATK-dev"><name>ATK-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling ATK applications</summary><description>
These are the ATK header files. They are required when compiling applications
that use the ATK library. ATK is an Accessibility Toolkit.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/GTKmm-dev.xml"><name>GTKmm-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling C++ GTK applications</summary><description>
These are the glibmm header files. They are required when compiling C++
applications that use the GTK, ATK or Pango libraries..</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/GLib-dev"><name>GLib-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling GLib applications</summary><description>
These are the GLib header files. They are required when compiling applications
that use the GLib library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/GLibmm-dev.xml"><name>GLibmm-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling C++ GLib applications</summary><description>
These are the glibmm header files. They are required when compiling C++
applications that use the GLib library.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/GTK-2.4.xml"><name>GTK-2.4</name><summary>set up a GTK 2.4 build environment</summary><description>
This program runs a command in an environment with PKG_CONFIG_PATH set to
include the location of the GTK 2.4 and related library headers. By default, it
runs /bin/sh to give you a shell.

Typical usage is to run this and then configure and build your program from the
new shell. The resulting binary should work on all systems with GTK 2.4 and
later.

Note: if you build your program using Zero Install then it's easier to just add
the GTK dependencies to the source interface file.</description><homepage>http://0install.net</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/2006/icons/gtk-logo.png" type="image/png"/><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/Pango-dev"><name>Pango-dev</name><summary>headers for compiling Pango applications</summary><description>
These are the Pango header files. They are required when compiling applications
that use the Pango library. Pango is a library for laying out and rendering of
text, with an emphasis on internationalization.</description></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/0publish"><name>0publish</name><summary>utility to make creating injector interfaces easier</summary><description>
0publish makes creating and modifying injector interface files easier. It can
create a new commented template for you or edit an existing one.

Various editing operations are available, the most basic being to let you edit
it in your preferred text editor. It automatically removes the signature when
loading an interface and creates a new one when writing it back out. It will
also validate the new version before saving it.

A tutorial on 0publish can be found at http://0install.net/injector-
packagers.html.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/0publish.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/interfaces/ZeroInstall-GUI.xml"><name>ZeroInstall-GUI</name><summary>graphical interface for the Zero Install injector</summary><description>
The Zero Install GUI displays a window showing which versions of various
components will be used when running a program, and allows you to alter various
policy settings to affect the selection process. You can use this to mark
particular versions of libraries as preferred, bugggy, etc.</description><homepage>http://0install.net/injector.html</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/3rd-party/Inkscape.xml"><name>Inkscape</name><summary>an SVG-based vector drawing application</summary><description>
Inkscape is an Open Source vector graphics editor, with capabilities similar to
Illustrator, Freehand, CorelDraw, or Xara X using the W3C standard Scalable
Vector Graphics (SVG) file format. Supported SVG features include shapes, paths,
text, markers, clones, alpha blending, transforms, gradients, patterns, and
grouping. Inkscape also supports Creative Commons meta-data, node editing,
layers, complex path operations, bitmap tracing, text-on-path, flowed text,
direct XML editing, and more. It imports formats such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, and
others and exports PNG as well as multiple vector-based formats.

Inkscape's main goal is to create a powerful and convenient drawing tool fully
compliant with XML, SVG, and CSS standards. We also aim to maintain a thriving
user and developer community by using open, community-oriented development.</description><homepage>http://inkscape.org/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/tests/Inkscape.png" type="image/png"/><category>Graphics</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/3rd-party/PySol.xml"><name>PySol</name><summary>a collection of more than 200 solitaire card games</summary><description>
PySol is an exciting collection of more than 200 solitaire card games. Its
features include support for lots of distinct games, very nice look and feel,
multiple cardsets and table tiles, sound and background music, unlimited undo &amp;
redo, load &amp; save games, player statistics and log files, hint system, demo
games, support for user written plug-ins, integrated HTML help browser and lots
of documentation.

Among the supported games are classics like Aces Up, Baker's Game, Canfield,
FreeCell, Forty Thieves, Golf, Klondike, Pyramid, Scorpion, Spider, Yukon, and
many more...

PySol is copyrighted OpenSource software distributed under the terms of the GNU
General Public License.

PySol is written in 100% pure Python</description><homepage>http://www.pysol.org/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/tests/pysol.png" type="image/png"/><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/3rd-party/GDC.xml"><name>GDC</name><summary>D Compiler for GCC</summary><description>
GDC is a D language front end for the GNU Compiler Collection. It supports a
number of targets and nearly all features of Digital Mars D.

D is a systems programming language. Its focus is on combining the power and
high performance of C and C++ with the programmer productivity of modern
languages like Ruby and Python. Special attention is given to the needs of
quality assurance, documentation, management, portability and reliability.

D is statically typed, and compiles direct to native code. It's multiparadigm:
supporting imperative, object oriented, and template metaprogramming styles.
It's a member of the C syntax family, and its look and feel is very close to
C++'s. For a quick feature comparison, see this comparison of D with C, C++, C#
and Java.</description><homepage>http://dgcc.sourceforge.net/</homepage><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/3rd-party/XaraXtreme.xml"><name>Xara Xtreme</name><summary>cross-platform vector artwork and photocomposition package</summary><description>
XaraLX is a vector graphics and photocomposition program. It is primarily a
vector graphics program, but it also handles photos and drawings. It has an
easy-to-use and easy-to-learn approach.</description><homepage>http://www.xaralx.org/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/XaraXtreme.png" type="image/png"/><category>Graphics</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/3rd-party/SCons.xml"><name>SCons</name><summary>a software construction tool</summary><description>
SCons is a software construction tool (build tool substitute for Make)
implemented in Python. It features a modular build engine that can be embedded
in other software. SCons configuration files are Python scripts that call the
build engine API.

It can scan files to detect dependencies automatically and maintain a global
view of all dependencies in a build tree, and uses MD5 signatures to detect
changed file contents reliably. Timestamps can be used if you prefer. SCons also
supports parallel builds and is easily extensible through user-defined builder
and scanner objects.</description><homepage>http://www.scons.org/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/tests/scons-logo.png" type="image/png"/><category>Development</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/3rd-party/Freetype2.xml"><name>Freetype2</name><summary>free, portable library for digital typography</summary><description>
FreeType 2 is a high-quality and portable font engine that is capable of
supporting several font formats (be they bitmapped or scalable) through a simple
and uniform interface. Its design is modular and allows independent &quot;font
driver&quot; modules to be added, even at runtime, to support additional formats. It
also provides a high-quality anti-aliasing renderer, an innovative auto-hinting
engine, and support for the following font formats: TrueType Type1, CID-Type 1,
Multiple Masters Type 1 OpenType/CFF, pure CFF, and CEF Windows FNT/FON.</description><homepage>http://www.freetype.org/</homepage></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/armagetronad.xml"><name>armagetronad</name><summary>a Tron clone in 3D</summary><description>
&quot;A Tron clone in 3D&quot;.

This has been the tagline of Armagetron, since, well, a very long time, and is
probably the shortest and most accurate description possible. Tron was an arcade
game based on the movie of the same name, release by Disney in 1982. The
original game consisted of 4 sub-games, the only one of concern is the 'Light
Cycles' one, in which the player uses a left/right joystick to control a 'Light
Cycle' which leaves a wall behind it wherever the cycle it goes, turning only at
90 degree angles. The player must then get the AI to crash into their wall while
avoiding hitting the AI's own wall themselves. Those were the humble beginnings
of Armagetron Advanced's game play, which has now blossomed into 16 player
mayhem, with highly advanced AI, network game play, and of course all in a 3D
environment.</description><homepage>http://www.armagetronad.net/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/armagetronad.png" type="image/png"/><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/Lincity.xml"><name>Lincity</name><summary>city simulation game</summary><description>
Lincity is a city simulation game. You are required to build and maintain a
city. You must feed, house, provide jobs and goods for your residents. You can
build a sustainable economy with the help of renewable energy and recycling, or
you can go for broke and build rockets to escape from a pollution ridden and
resource starved planet, it's up to you.</description><homepage>http://lincity.sourceforge.net/</homepage><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/vdrift.xml"><name>vdrift</name><summary>VDrift</summary><description>
VDrift is a realistic racing simulation with drifting in mind</description><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/Supertux.xml"><name>Supertux</name><summary>2D jump'n run sidescroller game</summary><description>
SuperTux is a classic 2D jump'n run sidescroller game in a style similar to the
original SuperMario games. The Milestone1 release of SuperTux features 9
enemies, 26 playable levels, software and OpenGL rendering modes, configurable
joystick and keyboard input, new music and completly redone graphics. Together
with a little story, we hope to provide a good gaming experince with this first
Milestone release.</description><homepage>http://supertux.berlios.de/</homepage><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/gtkdc.xml"><name>gtkdc</name><summary>client for the Direct Connect network</summary><description>
A client for the Direct Connect peer-to-peer network inspired by DC++.</description><homepage>http://www.gtkdc.org/</homepage><category>Network</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/OpenEuclide.xml"><name>OpenEuclide</name><summary>2D geometry software</summary><description>
OpenEuclide is a 2D geometry software: figures are defined dynamically by
describing formal geometrical constraints. This project is a basic tool for
educational or modeling purpose. It is distributed under the GNU GPL licence,
free and multi-platform (up to now, GNU and windows).</description><homepage>http://coulon.publi.free.fr/openeuclide</homepage><category>Education</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/opencity.xml"><name>opencity</name><summary>OpenCity Simulation Game</summary><description>
  OpenCity is a full 3D city simulator game project. It is written in standard
  C++ with OpenGL and SDL from scratch. It is not intended to be a clone of any
  famous city simulator from Max*s. So, if you are looking to download a free
  SimCity 4 like, please forget OpenCity. I work on it at my spare time, I
  really meant it &quot;my spare time&quot;!
  </description><homepage>http://www.opencity.info/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/opencity.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/Stellarium.xml"><name>Stellarium</name><summary>a beautiful night sky simulator</summary><description>
Stellarium is a free open source planetarium for your computer. It shows a
realistic sky in 3D, just like what you see with the naked eye, binoculars or a
telescope.

It is being used in planetarium projectors. Just set your coordinates and go.</description><homepage>http://www.stellarium.org/</homepage><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/Stellarium.png" type="image/png"/><category>Education</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/Abiword.xml"><name>abiword</name><summary>AbiWord Word Processor</summary><description>
AbiWord is a lightweight word processing application.</description><category>Office</category><icon href="http://0install.net/feed_icons/abiword.png" type="image/png"/></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/Solfege.xml"><name>solfege</name><summary>smarten your ears</summary><description>
Solfege is free music education software. Use it to train your rhythm, interval,
scale and chord skills. Solfege - Smarten your ears!</description><homepage>http://www.solfege.org</homepage><category>Audio</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/sear.xml"><name>sear</name><summary>Sear - a client for Worldforge</summary><description>
Sear is a client for MMORPGs using the Worldforge system.</description><category>Game</category></interface><interface uri="http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/SCOURGE.xml"><name>S.C.O.U.R.G.E.</name><summary>rogue-like game in the tradition of NetHack and Moria</summary><description>
S.C.O.U.R.G.E. is a rogue-like game in the fine tradition of NetHack and Moria.
It sports a graphical front-end, similar to glHack or the Falcon's eye. I tried
to design the 3D UI as a best of both worlds from old to new: It lets you rotate
the view, zoom in/out, view special effects, etc. On the other hand I've always
liked the old-school isometric games like Exult or Woodward</description><homepage>http://scourge.sourceforge.net/</homepage><category>Game</category></interface></c:catalog>
<!-- Base64 Signature
iQEcBAABCAAGBQJSFyQUAAoJEAcTP5bKdNi6MJ4IAJF5E6s9aqcQSuqMl7wAVmSA5KxMjKiySJWv
Xua3GMwrBxbZ8Q8G2w5xexzq/4/NwIDzY8IFW8MSYyjIhhoPYGg1xpp6x31GQzJAOqq3jU2UXW8a
JQremEyHzuYUnZy6tFrVDoE4ny5gbDDVQ3rg5uqAIEYAF2rkp3ctu7kvsfZQ86QDumu3GuKE58FD
NhO81jh7lUAMgvA1Rl9eLFGqO1K1IYh8LJRXAtlkKVgI8A01qi35yY8RExD64sdp2Yx/A07MsTmp
EHr8Fw8PLnltxEfkPK5l47EJKIT4eav6P1L05GypKl9J8wkKDC+A7mdqmFr4rnUmgIquws8cJMuA
+bE=

-->
