<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<div style='max-width: 60em'>

<h2>Distribution integration</h2>

<p>
If you have already installed a package using your distribution's installer then you may wish to use
that instead of downloading a second copy using Zero Install. 
Starting with <a href='injector.html'>Zero Install 0.29</a>, two methods are available to integrate
Zero Install packages with distribution ones:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><p>A distribution package can install a file named <b>/usr/share/0install.net/native_feeds/INTERFACE</b>.
  This is automatically used as an additional feed for INTERFACE (replace "/" characters in the package's
  interface URI with "#" characters).
  </p>
  
  <p>This is useful if the package installs the program as a self-contained
  directory somewhere. i.e. the installed package has the same format as the Zero Install package. If the
  package already contains a local feed file, you can just symlink to it directly.</p></li>

  <li>
  <p>
  A feed author can add a &lt;package-implementation package="name"/&gt; element to their feed. Zero Install
  will query your distribution's package manager to see if a package with this name is already installed. If so,
  that version will be considered as another candidate, with a stability rating
  of "packaged" (which is ranked between "stable" and "preferred").
  </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
For example, here is what happens if you ask to run AbiWord when you already
have the <b>libenchant1</b> library it requires installed using <b>apt-get</b>:
</p>

<pre>$ <b>0launch http://0install.net/2006/autopackage/Abiword.xml</b></pre>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img src='screens/abiword-have-enchant.png' width='657' height='274' alt='Abiword with native libenchant'/>
</p>

<p>
If Abiword is itself installed using <b>apt-get</b>, then the dialog is even simpler, and nothing needs to
be downloaded:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img src='screens/abiword-native.png' width='580' height='249' alt='Native Abiword'/>
</p>

<p>
Of couse, you are always free to change the selected version from the native package to a Zero Install
version. This will also happen autoamatically if your native version is incompatible with the required
version. For example, if you try this on a machine with a very old copy of libenchant1 then Zero Install
will download a newer version rather than using that one.
</p>

<p>
As always, all software installed by Zero Install goes in the cache directory and does not conflict with
files installed by the native package manager.
</p>

<h2>Future work</h2>

<p>
Distribution integration is not yet finished.
</p>

<p>
Since different distributions use different names for the same package we may need to allow distributions
to be named in the feed files. We may need a way to specify mappings for version numbers, to cope with different
versioning schemes.
</p>

<p>
We only consider native packages that are actually installed. We could also consider native packages
that are available (you'd need to enter the root password). This might be useful if no Zero Install version
was available, or if you preferred to use a native package for some reason.
</p>

<p>
Finally, Zero Install can only get package information from .deb-based systems
at present. RPM (and other systems) are not currently supported, although
adding support should be easy enough now that we have the framework.
</p>

</div>

</html>
