<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<h2>Documentation layout</h2>

<dl>
    <dt><a href='goals.html'>Goals</a></dt><dd>Sets out the problems that Zero Install aims to solve
    in more detail than on the front page.</dd>

    <dt><a href='howitworks.html'>Screenshots</a></dt><dd>What actually happens when you use software
    this way? An illustrated guide.</dd>

    <dt><a href='perspectives.html'>Perspectives</a></dt><dd>A series of short introductions, targetted at different people (novice users, power users, system administrators, developers and distributions).</dd>

    <dt><a href='flash.html'>Flash demos</a></dt><dd>Flash videos showing Zero Install being used.</dd>

    <dt><a href='matrix.html'>Comparison</a></dt><dd>A table of features and installation systems to
    show how they differ.</dd>

    <dt><a href='faq.html'>FAQ</a></dt><dd>Common questions answered.</dd>

    <dt><a href='injector-security.html'>Security</a></dt><dd>Describes Zero Install's security model and explains
    why it should be more secure than traditional installation methods.</dd>

    <dt><a href='sharing.html'>Sharing</a></dt><dd>How to configure Zero Install to share downloads automatically
    and safely between users, without requiring them to have root access.</dd>

    <dt><a href='walkthrough.html'>Manual walk-through</a></dt><dd>In this guide we install a program which is available through Zero Install, but without using the Zero Install software itself. Instead, we will perform each step manually, as an educational experience.</dd>

    <dt><a href='distribution-integration.html'>Distribution integration</a></dt><dd>Zero Install can also satisfy dependencies using packages installed using the distribution's packaging system. If the distribution package isn't installed, or the version isn't suitable, then it will download a Zero Install copy instead.</dd>

    <dt><a href='roadmap.html'>Roadmap</a></dt><dd>Where we've been and where we're going.</dd>

    <dt><a href='legal.html'>Legal issues</a></dt><dd>Thoughts about some legal issues relating to distributing software this way.</dd>

    <dt><a href='survey.html'>Survey results</a></dt><dd>A write-up of the 2007 survey results.</dd>

    <dt><a href='links.html'>Links</a></dt><dd>Links to related software.</dd>
</dl>

<p>
If you're looking for information about the <b>old</b> filesystem-based
version of Zero Install, see <a href='filesystem.html'>The /uri/0install
filesystem</a>.
</p>

<table class='quicklinks'>
 <tr>
  <td><a href='injector.html'><img src='tango/go-next.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/> <br/>Install it!</a></td>
  <td><a href='injector-security.html'><img src='tango/secure.png' alt='' width='39' height='48'/> <br/>Security</a></td>
  <td><a href='dev.html'><img src='tango/applications-development.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/> <br/>Developers</a></td>
  <td><a href='faq.html'><img src='tango/help-browser.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/> <br/>FAQ</a></td>
 </tr>
</table>

</html>
