<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>Screenshots</h2>

<p>
<a href='injector.html'>The injector</a> (<b>0launch</b>) is a small Python program. You ask it to run a program by giving
it the program's full name (a web address). The injector does <b>not</b> need
to be installed or run as root. It does <b>not</b> write to any shared
directories (like <b>/usr/bin</b> or <b>/usr/lib</b>). It stores downloads in a cache directory
so that you don't need to download anything twice, and programs can still be used when you are off-line.
</p>

<h3>Getting software</h3>

<table class='picturebullets'>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/find-url.png' alt='' width='256' height='171'/></td>
  <td><h3>Find a program you want to run on the web</h3>
      <p>If it's a Zero Install program, it will give the URL to use. In this
      example, you would drag <a href='http://people.freenet.de/LinuxCNC/0install/foobillard'>this
      FooBillard link</a> to your installer.</p>
      <p>
      The injector can be run manually (<b>0launch URL</b>), but it is normally
      invoked by another program. Some examples include:
      </p>
<ul>
 <li>ROX users will drag the link to <a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/AddApp'>AddApp</a>, creating a launcher application that uses the injector.</li>
 <li>Xfce users will drag the link to the <a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/node/269'>xfce4-panel</a> program, creating a launcher button that uses the injector.</li>
 <li>Shell users will run the <b>0alias</b> command, creating a shell short-cut that runs the injector.</li>
</ul>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/confirm-key.png' alt='' width='256' height='154'/></td>
  <td><h3>Confirm the keys</h3>
      <p>The injector downloads information about the program from the given address.</p>
      <p>It checks that the information is signed using a GPG key you trust, confirming first if not.
      Even if you don't know about this key yet, the injector may provide a hint if it's in its database.</p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/find-libraries.png' alt='' width='256' height='127'/></td>
  <td><h3>Finding libraries</h3>
  <p>The downloaded file says that <b>FooBillard</b> requires various libraries (libpng, SDL, and SDL-mixer).
Each library is identified by a web address (URL) in the same way that the main <b>FooBillard</b> program was.
The injector downloads information about them in the same way. Since they may
be written by different people and be on different sites, you may be asked to confirm more keys. The injector
displays a dialog box showing the program and all required libraries.</p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/versions.png' alt='' width='256' height='150'/></td>
  <td><h3>Confirming the versions</h3>
  <p>Next to each component (program or library), the injector displays the version it will download. If you
want to use a different version, you can change it here. You can either select versions manually, or change
your <i>policy</i>. For example, you can choose whether the injector prefers
versions that have been tested for a while, or always defaults to the newest one available. When you're
happy, click on <b>Execute</b>.
  </p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/download-foo.png' alt='' width='256' height='133'/></td>
  <td><h3>Downloading</h3>
  <p>The injector now downloads all the required archives (supported formats include tar.gz, tar.bz2, zip, 
RPM, deb and autopackage). It unpacks each one into its own directory and
checks its contents against the <i>cryptographic digest</i>
given in the (signed) interface file. If the archive has been changed since the interface file was signed,
the download will be rejected. If the archive hasn't been tampered with, it is stored in your cache directory
(<b>~/.cache/0install.net/implementations</b>) in its own subdirectory, named after the digest. This ensures
that no two downloads can conflict with each other.
  </p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/foo-billard.png' alt='' width='256' height='216'/></td>
  <td><h3>Running</h3>
  <p>Finally, the injector runs the program, setting any required environment
  variables (specified in the interface files) to let it find its libraries. Enjoy your new software!</p>
  </td>
 </tr>
</table>

<h3>Upgrading</h3>

<table class='picturebullets'>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/check-for-updates.png' alt='' width='256' height='108'/></td>
  <td><h3>Run the program normally</h3>
    <p>The injector remembers when you last checked each program for updates. If it's been too long
    (by default, one month) then it quickly checks to see if a newer version is available when the
    program is started. You can skip or disable the check if you prefer. If a new version is available,
    you'll be shown the same dialog box confirming the versions as when installing.
    </p>
   </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/change-version.png' alt='' width='256' height='190'/></td>
  <td><h3>Changing version manually</h3>
      <p>Your launcher should provide a way to get back to the versions box at any time. For example,
      a ROX user would right-click on the launcher and choose <b>Versions...</b>. A command-line user
      can use the <b>--gui</b> flag to <b>0launch</b>. This displays the same versions dialog box as
      before.
      </p>
  </td>
 </tr>
</table>

<h3>Uninstalling</h3>

<table class='picturebullets'>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/uninstall.png' alt='' width='256' height='121'/></td>
  <td><h3>Open the cache viewer</h3>
    <p>From the dialog box listing the versions, click on the <b>Cache</b> button to see what
    versions you have available in your cache. Select any you don't want and remove them.
    If you try to run a program after removing code it needs, it will just display the normal
    versions dialog box asking you to confirm the version you want to download, and you'll be
    able to fetch it again.
    </p>
   </td>
 </tr>
</table>

<table class='quicklinks'>
 <tr>
  <td><a href='injector.html'><img src='tango/go-next.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/> <br/>Install it!</a></td>
  <td><a href='injector-security.html'><img src='tango/secure.png' alt='' width='39' height='48'/> <br/>Security</a></td>
  <td><a href='dev.html'><img src='tango/applications-development.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/> <br/>Developers</a></td>
  <td><a href='faq.html'><img src='tango/help-browser.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/> <br/>FAQ</a></td>
 </tr>
</table>

</html>
