<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>The Zero Install Injector</h2>

<p>
The injector (<b>0launch</b>) is a small Python program. You ask it to run a program by giving
it the program's full name (a web address):
</p>

<ol>
<li>The injector downloads information about the program from the given address.</li>
<li>It checks that the information is signed using a GPG key you trust, confirming first if not.</li>
<li>It downloads information about any libraries the program needs in the same way. Libraries are also
named by web addresses, and may be written by different people and be on different sites.</li>
<li>It choose a sensible version of the program and of each required library, and prompts you to confirm or
change them.</li>
<li>It downloads an archive of the chosen version of each one.</li>
<li>Each archive is unpacked and its digest verified. If correct, it is stored in your cache directory. Each
archive is stored in a different subdirectory in the cache, so no two versions can conflict.</li>
<li>It runs the program, setting any required environment variables to let it find its libraries.</li>
</ol>

<p>
The injector does <b>not</b> need to be installed or run as root. It does
<b>not</b> write to any shared directories (like <b>/usr/bin</b> or
<b>/usr/lib</b>).
</p>

<p>
The injector can be run manually, but it is normally invoked by another program. Some examples include:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>When a ROX desktop user drags a link from a web-browser to the <a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/AddApp'>AddApp</a> program, it creates a launcher application that uses the injector.</li>
 <li>When an Xfce user drags a link from a web-browser to the <a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/node/269'>xfce4-panel</a> program, it creates a launcher button that uses the injector.</li>
 <li>When a shell user runs the <b>0alias</b> command, it creates a shell short-cut that runs the injector.</li>
</ul>

</html>
