<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<p style='text-align: center; padding: 0.5em'>
  <span class='note'>
  <strong>Quick start:</strong> <a href='injector.html'>Install 0launch now!</a>
  </span>
</p>

<p>
The Zero Install system aims to provide a better way of installing software than traditional systems (tarballs, apt-get,
bundles, setup.exe, etc). Here are some of our goals:
</p>

<dl class='spaced'>
 <dt>Anyone can install software</dt>
 <dd>You don't have to be root just to install a word-processor.</dd>

 <dt>Anyone can distribute software</dt>
 <dd>You don't need to be blessed by a distribution (or anyone else) to be part of Zero Install.</dd>

 <dt>It doesn't matter whether software is installed or not</dt>
 <dd>You just run it. Zero Install handles the rest (downloading and caching as needed).</dd>

 <dt>Downloads are shared</dt>
 <dd>If one user installs a 20 Mb application, another user can run it without downloading it again.</dd>

 <dt>Users don't need to trust each other</dt>
 <dd>If one user downloads a malicious program, other users aren't affected.</dd>
</dl>

<p>[ <a href='doc.html'>Read more...</a> ]</p>

<h2>Two implementations</h2>

<p>
We are experimenting with two different implementations of the above goals. Our first is the
<a href='filesystem.html'>Zero Install Filesystem</a>, which uses a Linux kernel module to provide
a virtual filesystem containing all software, fetched on demand. For example, you can run ROX-Filer
with this command:
</p>

<pre>
$ /uri/0install/rox.sourceforge.net/rox
</pre>

<div class='figure'>
  <img width="443" height="199" src="apps.png"
       alt='ROX-Filer window showing Memo application on the remote machine' />
  <p>Running Memo via the filesystem</p>
</div>

<p>
The first time you do this, Zero Install downloads ROX-Filer, saves it in the disk cache, and runs it. Running the command
again will start the filer instantly (no network access required).
</p>

<p>
The filesystem worked very well, and most of the ROX desktop is now available
this way. The problem was the need for the kernel module. Linux modules are
difficult to install, can't be distributed as binaries, only work on Linux,
need to be recompiled whenever the kernel is upgraded, and are a security risk
if buggy (sysadmins are reluctant to install them).
</p>

<p>
We addressed these issues by creating the <a href='injector.html'>Zero Install
Injector</a>, which is pure Python and doesn't even need root access to
install.
</p>

<div class='figure'>
  <img width="545" height="325" src="edit-injector.png"
     alt="Running Edit with the injector" />
  <p>Running Edit with the injector</p>
</div>

</html>
