<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html>

<div>

<table class='picturebullets' style='margin: 0px'>
 <tr class='summary'>
  <td class='image'><img src='tango/package-x-generic.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/></td>
  <td><h3>Anyone can install software</h3>
      <p>You don't have to be the <k>administrator</k> just to <k>install a word-processor</k> <more href='goals.html#anyoneinstall'/></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr class='summary'>
  <td class='image'><img src='tango/applications-internet.png' alt='' width='48' height='48'/></td>
  <td><h3>Anyone can distribute software</h3>
      <p>You don't need to be <k>blessed by a distribution</k> (or anyone else) to be part of Zero Install;<br/>
      The system is <k>completely decentralised</k> <more href='goals.html#anyonedistrib'/></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr class='summary'>
  <td class='image'><img src='tango/update.png' alt='' width='48' height='46'/></td>
  <td><h3>Automatic updates</h3>
    <p>When updates are available, Zero Install will notify you<more href='goals.html#updates'/></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr class='summary'>
  <td class='image'><img src='tango/secure.png' alt='' width='39' height='48'/></td>
  <td><h3>Security</h3>
      <p>If one user downloads a <k>malicious</k> program, <k>other users</k> aren't affected;<br/>
      Users can <k>share</k> downloads without having to <k>trust</k> each other;<br/>
      Installation does not <k>execute</k> any of the downloaded code;<br/>
      <k>Digital signatures</k> are always checked before new software is run <more href='injector-security.html'/></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
</table>

<quicklinks>
  <link href='doc.html' img='tango/book.png'>Read more</link>
  <link href='dev.html' img='tango/applications-development.png'>Developers</link>
  <link href='faq.html' img='tango/help-browser.png'>FAQ</link>
  <mainlink>@AUTO_DOWNLOAD_HTML@</mainlink>
</quicklinks>
</div>

<div style='text-align: center; float: right; padding: 2em;'>
<video vid='Lu0MAiNIaGM'>Zero Install introduction</video>
</div>

<div class='news'>

<h2>Help Wanted!</h2>
<p>
<a href='https://features.opensuse.org/310040'>OpenSUSE packager needed</a>. An RPM already exists in their build service, but someone needs to get it into the main repository. If you'd like to help with this (or anything else), please introduce yourself on our friendly <a href='support.html'>mailing list</a>!</p>

<h2>News</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Jun 2010</dt><dd>The big news this month is the new support for <a href='http://www.packagekit.org/'>PackageKit</a> - if a Zero Install program depends on an uninstalled distribution package, Zero Install can use PackageKit to install it, using the distribution's native package manager. The new <a href='0test.html'>0test</a> now has HTML output to show the test results matrix as a colourful table.</dd>
<dt>May 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3267'>0launch 0.48</a> (and 0.47) released, with support for selecting downloads by language, support for native Slackware and FreeBSD packages as dependencies. Development of <a href='http://0install.de'>the .NET version</a> continues.</dd>
<dt>Apr 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3090'>0launch 0.46 released</a>, with the new SAT solver. Feeds for <a href='http://repo.roscidus.com/devel/pkg-config'>pkg-config</a> and <a href='http://repo.roscidus.com/devel/make'>make</a> are now available so they can be used as build dependencies with <a href='0compile.html'>0compile</a>. <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3126'>Distribution integration for Gentoo and FreeBSD Ports</a> has been added. An <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3109'>OpenOffice.org feed</a> is under development.</dd>
<dt>Mar 2010</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.45</a> released, with support for native Gentoo packages and distribution-specific package names, better support for alternative digest algorithms and better support for pathnames on Windows. A new <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3082'>SAT solver</a> has been implemented, which can select the best set of versions in every situation. <a href='http://roscidus.com/0mirror/'>The feed mirror site</a> has been greatly upgraded, with per-user and per-site lists of feeds and rankings.</dd>
<dt>Feb 2010</dt><dd><a href='install-windows.html'>The Windows version</a> is coming along nicely - please help to test it! Also, <a href='0export.html'>0export 0.1</a> was released; this allows easy creation of bundles for off-line distribution or archiving.</dd>
<dt>Jan 2010</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.44</a> released. Improvements include a progress display in console mode, support for GnuPG 2, canonicalisation of architectures and some minor bug-fixes.</dd>
<dt>Dec 2009</dt><dd>The Sugar project has also provided <a href='http://article.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/2866'>experimental PackageKit integration</a>. <a href='http://repo.roscidus.com'>repo.roscidus.com</a> now hosts Java 6 (JRE and JDK), SWT and E packages.</dd>
<dt>Nov 2009</dt><dd>A new Zero Install repository has been set up on <a href='http://repo.roscidus.com'>repo.roscidus.com</a> to host feeds for programs where the upstream authors don't provide one. 0launch 0.43 was released, with support for xz compression, gettings feeds over https and a Spanish translation.</dd>
<dt>Oct 2009</dt><dd>Lots of <a href='http://www.mail-archive.com/sugar-devel@lists.sugarlabs.org/msg09868.html'>interesting discussion</a> between Sugar Labs (One Laptop per Child) and Zero Install developers about using Zero Install to distribute Sugar Activities. The project has also offered us hosting to set up a repository for third-party packages (i.e. those where the upstream project isn't interested in providing packages of their own). Meanwhile, the grid.dk project has written up <a href='http://old.nabble.com/gobject-dependencies-for-CLI-mode--tt25810119.html#a25810119'>some instructions</a> for using Zero Install to deploy Grid applications. <a href='deb2zero.html'>deb2zero</a> has been merged with rpm2zero to form <a href='http://old.nabble.com/pkg2zero-%28deb2zero-%2B-rpm2zero%29-tt26048471.html'>pkg2zero</a>.</dd>
<dt>Sep 2009</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.42</a> released. The new version has better internationalisation support, and is able to look up GPG key information from a server. The default service informs you if the feed is signed by a member of the Debian project, in addition to showing information from the old database. We hope to add other trust sources in the future. <a href='distribution-integration.html'>Distribution integration</a> now also works with multi-arch RPMs. libglade is no longer a dependency. The experimental Windows branch is now <a href ='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/2590/focus=2598'>able to run Seamonkey</a>.</dd>
<dt>Jul 2009</dt><dd>No release this month, but work includes much improved <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/2489'>internationalisation support</a>, support for <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/2506'>key information servers</a>, and support for <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/2515'>GtkBuilder</a>.</dd>
<dt>Jun 2009</dt><dd>An experimental <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/2390'>Firefox extension for Zero Install</a> is now available.<br/>
<a href='0compile.html'>0compile 0.18</a> adds a GUI to the "autocompile" feature and introduces more support for compiling legacy source code.</dd>
<dt>May 2009</dt><dd><a href='0release.html'>0release 0.10</a> automatically creates binary packages along with the source releases.<br/>
Added <a href='http://sourceforge.net/apps/ideatorrent/zero-install/ideatorrent/most_popular_ever/'>IdeaTorrent</a> to track popular ideas - open for voting now!</dd>
<dt>Apr 2009</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.40</a> released (fixes FTP support with Python 2.6).<br/>
The new <a href='0compile.html'>0compile autocompile</a> feature will download source code and build and register the binary in one go, along with any dependencies.</dd>
<dt>Mar 2009</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.39</a> released, with support for translations, improved background updates and better support for the RPM and Fink package managers.</dd>
<dt>Jan 2009</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.38</a> released, with better support for sudo, and a new "0store audit" command to check the whole cache.
<br/>The <a href='0export.html'>0export</a> command is now much improved, with a simple GUI.</dd>
</dl>

<p>For more information see the <a href='support.html'>mailing list archives</a> or the <a href='http://www.gnomefiles.org/version.php?soft_id=921'>release notes on gnomefiles.org</a>. There's also a <a href='http://twitter.com/talex5'>Twitter feed</a>.
</p>

</div>

</html>
