<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>The Injector: Design</h2>

<p>
This page describes the design of the injector.
</p>

<p>
Everything 0install downloads from the net currently goes in <b>~/.cache/0install.net/</b>.
Every archive it downloads unpacks into its own directory inside this. So,
there's one directory for ROX-Filer, and another for ROX-Session, etc. In fact,
there's one directory for every version of ROX-Filer, if you want more than one
available. Every directory is uniquely named, so you'll never get conflicts
when trying to install two different programs.
</p>

<p>
The injector doesn't store anything else, except a few config details
(such as whether you want to check for updates automatically), which go in
<b>~/.config/0install.net/</b>. The goal is to be as non-invasive as possible, so that
installation never causes any mysterious messing with other files all over the
disk that happens with some installation systems.
</p>

<p>
The idea is that you don't need to back up <b>~/.cache</b>, because you can
always download the stuff again. For example, if you delete the whole
<b>~/.cache/0install.net/</b> directory and then click on ROX-Filer, it will just prompt you
to download it again. The cache is just to make things faster (and work when
offline), but you don't really need to worry about it. You shouldn't
modify anything in there.
</p>

<p>
In future, Zero Install will store downloaded implementations in <b>/var/cache/0install.net/</b>
instead of in your home directory. This allows sharing between users. The use of cryptographic
digests (described below) makes this safe; users don't need to trust each other not to put
malicious code in the shared cache.
</p>


<h2>Requirements</h2>

<p>
The injector has the same overall goals as Zero Install:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Any user can run any program they want, without it needing to be
installed first.</li>
<li>Users refer to programs by globally unique names (URLs). So, a
user asks to run "http://gimp.org/gimp", rather than the rather vague
"The Gimp".</li>
<li>Users can run whatever version of a program they want.</li>
<li>Users don't need the root password.</li>
<li>Users don't need to trust each other.</li>
<li>The system administrator doesn't have to trust the users.</li>
<li>Any developer can make software available through the system (without
needing the blessing of some distribution first).</li>
</ul>

<h2>Security and sharing</h2>

<p>
To clarify the security requirements: the injector is designed to support
this situation:
</p>

<ul>
<li>There are two users.</li>
<li>The system administrator doesn't trust either with root permission.</li>
<li>The users don't trust each other.</li>
<li>Both users want to run (the same version of) the Gimp.</li>
<li>The Gimp must only be downloaded and stored on disk once.</li>
</ul>

<p>
Current systems make you choose either:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Inefficient (two copies downloaded and installed), or</li>
<li>Insecure (second user must trust first user to get and install a good
  copy).</li>
</ul>

<p>
Although this situation obviously occurs in schools, libraries, etc,
solving it is also useful in the home. Although you might expect family
members to trust each other, remember that trust includes trusting them
not to get infected with viruses, etc. If my brother gets some spyware
and then installs the Gimp, I shouldn't get infected too. This also
applies if you're doing sandboxing within a single user account, or
using a dedicated 'sandbox' user for some tasks.
</p>

<h3>The injector's solution</h3>

<p>
First, users need some way to specify what they want to run exactly.
"Run the Gimp" is too vague (good gimp or evil gimp?), so we use URLs
(like autopackage).
</p>

<p>
If both users say "Run gimp.org/gimp" then the system is smart enough to
only get it once. If one user says "Run evil.com/gimp" and one says "Run
gimp.org/gimp", the system downloads both programs.
</p>

<p>
Clearly, something has to actually download the software. It can either
be one of the users, or a system daemon.
</p>

<p>
Traditional Zero Install uses a system daemon running as its own user.
Both users know that /uri/0install/gimp.org/gimp has been downloaded
faithfully from gimp.org, because only the daemon can make things appear
there and it won't do anything else.
</p>

<p>
Injector Zero Install has one of the users download the software. This
is nicer, because they can do things like use a mirror or a CD to get the
archives. The user uses a setuid (to 'zeroinstall') program to copy the
downloaded (unpacked) directory into the cache. The helper generates a
digest of the whole directory structure (the SHA1 of the manifest file,
which contains the directory structure and the SHA1 sums of all the
files inside it) and puts the directory in the cache named with the
digest (/var/cache/zero-install/sha1=8374ab3254...).
</p>

<p>
When user B wants to run the Gimp, 0launch gets the SHA1 sum for
gimp.org/gimp and looks to see if it's in the cache. If it is, the user
knows that it is the copy they wanted (since the helper won't copy
modified versions into the cache under that digest name). Everything in
the cache is owned by zeroinstall, and no user (or virus ;-) has write
access to it.
</p>

<h2>Policies</h2>

<p>
A running process is created by combining many different libraries (and other components).
In the Zero Install world, we have all versions of each library available at
all times. The problem then is how to choose which versions to use.
Some examples of ways to choose:
</p>
<ul>
<li>The very latest version.</li>
<li>The latest version in the cache (eg, when off-line).</li>
<li>The latest stable version.</li>
<li>The version recommended by your distribution.</li>
<li>A version not affected by a known security flaw.</li>
<li>The version you've always used in the past.</li>
<li>A development version you are working on yourself.</li>
</ul>
<p>
One way to organise things is to have a component link directly to particular
versions of the components on which it depends. So, running Memo 2.0.0 might
always use pygtk-2.0.0 and Python 2.2.0. But we often want to use the same component
with different versions of its dependencies. For example, when Python 2.2.1
comes out with bug-fixes, we will want Memo to use it automatically. 
</p>

<p>
Zero Install solved this in the past by means of the <b>latest</b> symlinks. Here,
Memo 2.0.0 uses <b>python.org/latest</b>, which is always a symlink to the latest
version. But this isn't flexible enough to cope with the list of cases above.
What if Python 2.2.1 is available, but we'd rather continue with 2.2.0 than
download it? The <b>0divert</b> command allows the root user to redirect these
symlinks, but a major goal of Zero Install is to make software use easy without
involving an administrator. Also, <b>0divert</b> affects all users, whereas we only
wish to affect one user, or maybe even only one program.
</p>

<p>
The injector solves this problem by selecting components to meet a program's requirements,
according to rules specified by the user:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="569" height="364" src="inject.png"
     alt="The injector selects versions according to the user's policy" />
</p>

<h2>Interfaces and Implementations</h2>

<dl>
<dt>An interface</dt>
<dd>describes what something does (eg, "Simple text editor").</dd>

<dt>An implementation</dt>
<dd>is something that does it (eg, Edit-1.9.6 or Edit-1.9.7).</dd>
</dl>
<p>
In Zero Install, interfaces are named by globally unique URLs (like web pages). Some examples
of interfaces are:
</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit">http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit</a></li>
<li><a href="http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/ROX-Lib">http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/ROX-Lib</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
Each <i>implementation</i> of an interface is identified by a cryptographic digest, eg:
</p>
<ul>
<li><b>sha1=235cb9dd77ef78ef2a79abe98f1fcc404bba4889</b></li>
<li><b>sha1=c86d09f1113041f5eaaa8c3d1416fcf4dad8e2e0</b></li>
</ul>

<p>
When we run a program (like Edit) we need to choose an implementation of every
interface on which it depends. Then, we need to tell the program where to find
them all; this process is known as <i>Dependency Injection</i> (or <i>Inversion
of Control</i>).</p>

<p>
Both tasks are handled by the injector. This takes as input an interface and
chooses an implementation based on the your policy.
</p>

<p>
The list of implementations of an interface is found by using the interface's name as a
URL and downloading the XML file it names (click on one of the interfaces above to see
what an interface file looks like).
</p>
<h2>Versions</h2>

<p>
An implementation (in the Zero Install sense) is always some particular
version. In future, we will identify implementations with a cryptographic hash
of their contents in addition to their version number. Therefore, two releases
with the same version number are still considered as separate implementations
if they differ in any way.
</p>

<p>
A version is a dot-separated list of integers. Eg "1.2.3". It can be just a
single number ("1") or a sequence of any number of components ("1.4.2.3").
Versions are ordered like this:
</p>

<ul>
<li>1</li>
<li>1.1</li>
<li>1.2</li>
<li>1.2.1</li>
<li>1.2.1.4</li>
<li>1.2.2</li>
<li>3</li>
</ul>

<p>
The injector doesn't care about anything other than the sort order (i.e., whether
one version comes before or after another). It is assumed that an
implementation can be safely replaced by one with a later version number, but
not with an earlier one. So, if you ask for "1.2.1" then you might get "1.2.2"
or "1.3" or even "5.7", but not "1.2.0". This is a little different to some
other systems, where numbers in different places have different meanings.
</p>

<p>
Incompatible changes (where a newer version cannot be used in place of an older
version) to an interface should be handled by creating a new interface. Eg:
</p>

<ul>
<li>/uri/0install/gtk.org/gtk/gtk-1.2.xml  (contains 1.2.0, 1.2.1, 1.2.2, ...)</li>
<li>/uri/0install/gtk.org/gtk/gtk-2.0.xml  (contains 2.0.0, 2.0.1, 2.2.0, 2.4.0, 2.4.1, ...)</li>
</ul>

<h2>Stability</h2>

<p>
The interface file should also give a stability rating for each implementation. The following
levels are allowed:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Stable</li>
<li>Testing</li>
<li>Developer</li>
<li>Buggy</li>
<li>Insecure</li>
</ul>

<p>
Stability ratings are kept independently of the implementations, and are expected to change over
time. When any new release is made, its stability should be set to <b>Testing</b>. Users who
have selected <b>Help test new versions</b> will then start using it. Other users will continue
with the previous stable release. After a while (days, weeks or months, depending on the project)
with no serious problems found, the implementation's stability can be changed to <b>Stable</b>
so that everyone will use it.
</p>

<p>
If problems are found, it can instead be marked as <b>Buggy</b>, or <b>Insecure</b>. The injector
won't select either by default, but it is useful to users to see the reason (users may opt to
continue using a buggy version if it seems to work for them, but they should never use an insecure
one). <b>Developer</b> is like a more extreme version of <b>Testing</b>, where the program is
expected to have bugs.
</p>

<p>
You can use the <b>Preferred Stability</b> setting in the interface dialog to choose which
versions to use. You can also change the stability rating of any implementation by clicking on it
and choosing a new rating from the popup menu. User-set ratings are shown in capitals.
</p>

<p>
As you make changes to the policy and ratings, the order of the implementations in the list
will change. The version at the top is the one that the injector will actually use. In addition
to the ratings about, you can set the rating to <b>Preferred</b>. Such versions always come first,
unless they're not cached and you are in Off-line mode.
</p>

<p>
Note: If you want to use the second item on the list because the first is
buggy, for example, then it is better to mark the first version as buggy than to mark the
second as preferred. This is because when a new version is available, you will want that to
become the version at the top of the list, whereas a preferred version will always be first.
</p>
 
<h2>Dependencies</h2>

<p>
The interface file also lists the dependencies of each implementation; the
injector locates an implementation of each dependency, recursively. All
information about dependencies is handled at the interface level; this is
because the same implementation may be used in different ways. Also, for
software not specially designed for use with the injector, it allows us to keep
the implementation in its original form.
</p>

<p>
This diagram shows some dependencies for Memo (the dotted lines):
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="554" height="345" src="depend.png"
     alt='Interface files give implementations and dependencies' />
</p>

<p>
The injector will also examine the dependencies of ROX-Lib and Python
recursively.
</p>

<h2>Running the injector on itself</h2>

<p>
The injector's GUI is just another application, and is fetched using the
injector. You can therefore edit the policy for the GUI using the GUI:
</p>

<pre>
$ 0launch -dg http://0install.net/2005/interfaces/injector-gui
</pre>

</html>
