<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>Injector FAQ</h2>

<p>
For questions about Zero Install in general, see the
<a href='faq.html'>general FAQ</a>.
</p>

<toc level='h3'/>

<h3>I haven't tried it yet, but it sounds really complicated</h3>
<p>It isn't. <a href='injector.html'>Try it</a>. Now.</p>

<h3>How do I provide software using Zero Install?</h3>

<p>You need to be able to upload some static files to a web server.</p>

<p>See the <i> <a href='injector-packagers.html'>Injector Packaging Guide</a></i>
for details.</p>

<h3>Doesn't it require a fast Internet connection?</h3>

<p>
No more than downloading programs from the Internet normally. However, it can
still save you some time, since it might only download the documentation for
a package when you click on Help, for example. With traditional systems, all the
extras have to get installed with the main program because users can't install
anything themselves later if they find they need it.
</p>

<p>
When you consider that users always need the <i>ability</i> to read a program's
documentation, use a particular export filter, etc, but rarely do so for any given
version of any particular program, you can see that the savings can be quite large.
</p>

<h3>What about people without Internet connections?</h3>

<p>
The injector provides the <b>0store</b> command for this purpose
(<b>man 0store</b> for details). This allows you to import a large program
into the cache from a CD.
</p>

<p>
If you have no network connection at all, you'll need to import the interface too,
using <b>0launch --import interface.xml</b>.
</p>

<h3>Isn't is really hard to find applications if you always have to
type URIs for them?</h3>

<p>Yes. As with the web, that works but it's not the intended way to
do it. Like the web, you have links to the URIs, and you use the links
normally.</p>
<p>
For example, you can run <b>0alias</b> to let you run programs quickly
from the shell, or
<a href="http://rox.sourceforge.net/phpwiki/index.php/AddApp">AddApp</a>
to create graphical launchers, for example.
</p><p>
You could put a shortcut on the pinboard, set a keyboard shortcut, or add it
to your Start menu.
</p>

<h3>What about when resources move?</h3>
<p>Everything you've already accessed at least once will continue to
work. Users trying software for the first time will find that it
doesn't work due to broken links. This is not new, either. The download
instructions for ROX-Filer tell users that they need to get GTK from
www.gtk.org and libxml from www.xmlsoft.org. If those sites change
their names, the download instructions will be broken. It really
doesn't make any difference.
As with the regular web, people can leave redirections to the new
site.</p>

<p>
The <b>0launch --import</b> command lets you import the interface from the
new location, and <b>0store</b> allows adding any archive to the cache (provided
its message digest matches).
</p>

<h3>How secure is this?</h3>
<p>About as secure as any system which ultimately involves running
software written by people you don't know who live in far away
countries. However, since the downloading is automatic, there are more
chances for automatic checking (eg, verifying GPG signatures, etc).
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="576" height="363" src="trustbox.png"
     alt='You are asked to confirm each new key'/>
</p>

<p>
To be more precise, it has all the advantages of application
directories (no install step, so no chance for anything to run as
root). In addition, if two users try to run the same application, they
both automatically get the same cached copy, whereas without this each
would have to install a separate copy to their home directory, or one
user has to trust the other user not to have modified his copy, and
use that.
</p>
<p>
See the <a href='injector-security.html'>injector security issues</a> document
for more information.
</p>

<h3>What if something gets automatically removed from the cache while
I'm up a mountain with my laptop?</h3>

<p>Currently, nothing is ever automatically removed from the cache.
Users can choose the purging scheme that suits them. For users with
broadband, that might mean removing anything that hasn't been accessed
for a year. For users with dial-up and 80Gb disks, that probably means
never ever removing anything.
</p>

<h3>How can I run my own version of something, instead of downloading a released version?</h3>

<p>
Let's say you want to run a CVS (developer) version of Edit. Start by checking out the latest
version from CVS, as normal (just press Return when asked for a password):
</p>

<pre>
$ cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/rox login
$ cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/rox co -P Edit
</pre>

<p>
Now, if you try to run it directly, it will probably complain that it can't find ROX-Lib (a library
it needs). The required libraries are listed in the <b>Edit.xml</b> file, and you can run that
using <b>0launch</b>:
</p>

<pre>
$ cd Edit
$ ./AppRun
*** This program needs ROX-Lib2 (version 1.19.14) to run.
$ 0launch Edit.xml
[ edit runs ]
</pre>

<p>
Of course, you could do <b>0alias edit-cvs Edit.xml</b> to make a command that runs this version
easily.
</p>

<h3>How can I register my own version under the original's URI?</h3>

<p>
The answer to the last question showed how to run a local version of a program directly, using 0launch
to fetch the libraries it needed. However, if you (or some other program) run Edit using the normal
URI (<b>http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit</b>), your version won't show up. To add it,
use <b>--feed</b> (<b>--add-feed</b> on older versions):
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>cd Edit</b>
$ <b>0launch --feed Edit.xml</b>
Feed 'Edit.xml':

1) Add as feed for 'http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit'

Enter a number, or CTRL-C to cancel [1]: 

Feed list for interface 'Edit' is now:
- /home/talex/Projects/Edit/Edit.xml

$ <b>0launch -g http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit</b>
</pre>

<p>
When the GUI opens, you should see your local copy listed (versions ending in .0
conventionally indicate snapshot versions).
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="754" height="302" src="edit-cvs.png"
     alt='The injector GUI showing the Snapshot version of Edit' />
</p>

<p>
This is particularly useful for libraries, since they are always used by other programs rather
than run directly.
</p>

</html>
