<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html lang="en">

<h2>Packaging guide</h2>

<p>
  To make software available through 0install, you need to publish a signed
  "feed" XML file on your web page. This file lists the available versions and
  their dependencies and says how to run the program. There are lots of ways to
  create this XML file.
</p>

<p>
  To see an example of the XML, go to any 0install program's feed in your browser
  (e.g. <a href='http://0install.net/tools/0export.xml'>0export</a>) and <i>View Page Source</i>.
</p>

<p>
  Before you start, have a look at <a href='packaging-concepts.html'>Understanding 0install: important concepts</a> to make
  sure you understand some key terms and ideas.
</p>

<p><strong>I want to...</strong></p>

<dt>
  <dt>... publish an XML file for an existing binary release</dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li>Read the <a href='packaging-binaries.html'>binary packaging guide</a>. This tutorial shows how to create an XML
	file describing the Blender 3D-animation application. The binary
	archive is published by the upstream authors and requires no
	modifications.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </dd>

  <dt>... publish XML for a source release</dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li>Start by reading the <a href='packaging-binaries.html'>binary packaging guide</a>. Most of the steps are the same.</li>
      <li>Read the <a href='0compile.html'>0compile user guide</a> to understand how users compile 0install software.</li>
      <li>Read the <a href='0compile-dev.html'>0compile developer guide</a> for a tutorial showing how to publish the GNU Hello example package.</li>
    </ul>
  </dd>

  <dt>... create an XML file describing my own software</dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li>Read the <a href='0release.html'>0release</a> documentation, which shows how to add a local feed to your source repository. Users can use this to run your program from a Git checkout, and you can use it to generate new releases automatically.</li>
      <li>Have a look at the <a href='templates.html'>template projects</a> for examples in various programming languages (Python, Java, C).</li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
</dt>

<h2>Other useful documentation</h2>

<dl>
 <dt><a href='interface-spec.html'>Feed specification</a></dt>
 <dd>The specification of the XML format.</dd>

 <dt><a href='tools.html'>Tools</a></dt>
 <dd>An index of the tools provided by the 0install project for generating feeds.</dd>
</dl>

</html>
