<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>The Injector: Specifications</h2>

<p>
This document is a formal description of the two injector file formats: the interface XML file
format and the manifest file format.
</p>

<toc level='h2'/>

<h2>Interfaces</h2>

<p>
Interface files are introduced in the <a href='injector-packagers.html'>packager's guide</a>.
They have the following syntax (? follows optional items, * means zero-or-more, order of elements
is not important, and extension elements can appear anywhere as long as they use a different
namespace):
</p>

<pre>
&lt;?xml version='1.0'?&gt;
&lt;interface xmlns='http://zero-install.sourceforge.net/2004/injector/interface'
	   uri='...' ?
	   main='...' ?&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;...&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;...&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;...&lt;/description&gt;

  &lt;icon type='...' href='...'/&gt; *
  &lt;feed src='...' arch='...'/&gt; *
  &lt;feed-for interface='...'/&gt; *

  [group] *
  [implementation] *

&lt;/interface&gt;
</pre>

<h3>Group</h3>

<p>
A group has this syntax:
</p>

<pre>
  &lt;group version='...' ?
       	  released='...' ?
	  main='...' ?
          stability='...' ?
          arch='...' ? &gt;
    [requires] *
    [group] *
    [implementation] *
  &lt;/group&gt;
</pre>

<h3>Implementation</h3>

<p>
An implementation has this syntax (an unspecified argument is inherited from
the closest ancestor &lt;group&gt; which defines it):
</p>

<pre>
  &lt;implementation
	id='...'
  	version='...' ?
	main='...' ?
  	released='...' ?
	stability='...' ?
	arch='...' ? &gt;
    &lt;archive
      href='...'
      size='...'
      extract='...' ? /&gt; *
  &lt;/implementation&gt;
</pre>

<h3>Requires</h3>

<p>
A &lt;requires&gt; element means that every implementation within the same group (including nested
sub-groups) requires an implementation of the specified interface when run. The injector will choose a
suiteable implementation, downloading one if required.
</p>

<p>
The location of the chosen implementation is passed to the program by setting environment variables,
as specified by the &lt;environment&gt; elements (typically, there will be exactly one of these in each
&lt;requires&gt; element). Each environment element gives the name of the variable and the relative path
of the item within the implementation to insert into the variable's value. The absolute path of the
item is prepended to the current value of the variable, separated by a colon character. If the
environment variable is not currently set then the path is prepended to the
value of the default attribute. If no default value is given either then the
environment variable's value is set to the absolute path directly.
</p>

<pre>
  &lt;requires
	interface='...'&gt;
    &lt;environment
	  name='...'
	  insert='...'
	  default='...' ? /&gt; *
  &lt;/requires&gt;
</pre>

<p>
For example, &lt;environment name='PATH' insert='bin'/&gt; would perform something similar to the
bash shell statement <b>export PATH=/path/to/impl/bin:$PATH</b>.
</p>

<h3>Metadata</h3>

<p>
All elements can contain extension elements, provided they are not in the Zero
Install namespace used by the elements defined here. The injector does not
currently make use of these elements itself, but other programs may find them
useful. In future, some of these may be used (for example, the GUI may display
the license terms).
</p>

<p>
The use of <a href='http://dublincore.org'>Dublin Core</a> is suggested for the following concepts, which
have the following meanings when found as a direct child of a &lt;group&gt; or &lt;implementation&gt; element:
</p>

<dl>
<dt>dc:creator</dt>
<dd>The primary author of the program.</dd>

<dt>dc:publisher</dt>
<dd>The person who created this implementation. For a binary, this is the person who
compiled it.</dd>

<dt>dc:license</dt>
<dd>License terms (a URI for the license is suggested).</dd>

</dl>

<p>
Other Dublin Core terms that may be useful include contributor,
dateCopyrighted, language, rights and rightsHolder.
</p>

<p>
These terms are not required as they are duplicated by the core Zero Install terms: identifier (id),
available (released) and requires (requires).
</p>

<p>
The source element may be used in future to record the source interface used to build this implementation.
</p>


<h2>Manifest files</h2>

<p>
Implementations are identified by an algorithm name (e.g., "SHA1"), and digest
of their contents calculated using that algorithm. Adding, deleting, renaming
or modifying any file in a tree will change its digest. It should be unfeasibly
difficult to generate a new tree with the same digest as a given tree. Thus, if you
know the digest of the implementation you want, and someone gives you a tree with
that digest, you can trust that it is the implementation you want.
</p>

<p>
Currently, "SHA1" is the only supported algorithm. The are known to be some weaknesses in
SHA1 which may allow an attacker to generate two different trees with the same digest, but
the attacker <i>must</i> get to generate both trees, so this not believed to be a security
risk at present. However, support for other algorithms may be added in the future (probably
when Python comes with support for them).
</p>

<p>
When checking a new tree (e.g., that has just been downloaded from the net and
unpacked), the injector generates a 'manifest' file. The manifest lists every
file, directory and symlink in the tree, and gives the SHA1 digest of each
file's content. Here is a sample manifest file for a tree containing two files
(<b>README</b> and <b>src/main.c</b>):
</p>

<pre>
F 0a4d55a8d778e5022fab701977c5d840bbc486d0 1132502750 11 README
D 1132502769 /src
F 83832457b29a423c8e6daf05c6dbcba17d0514dd 1132502769 17 main.c
</pre>

<p>
If you generate a manifest file for a directory tree and find that it is identical
to the manifest file you want, then you can feel confident that you have the tree you
want. This is convenient, because the manifest file is much smaller than the packaged tree.
To save even more space, we can simply compare the SHA1 digests of the manifest files, rather
than comparing the files themselves.  The top-level directory is renamed to this final digest
(so the <b>main.c</b> above would be stored as
<b>.../sha1=b848561cd89be1b806ee00008a503c63eb4ad56e/src/main.c</b>, for example).
</p>

<p>
After checking, the generated manifest file is stored in a file called
<b>.manifest</b> in the top-level of the tree. This is not strictly necessary, but if the tree
is modified later somehow it can show you exactly which files were changed (rather than just letting
you know that the tree has changed in some unknown way).
</p>

<p>
This description of the manifest file is based on Joachim's 12 Oct 2005 post to
the zero-install-devel list:
</p>

<p>
The manifest file lists, line by line, all nodes in a directory 
identified as "/", without "/" itself.  All relevant numbers are coded 
as decimal numbers without leading zeros (unless 0 is to be coded, which 
is coded as "0"). Times are represented as the number of seconds since 
the epoch. Nodes are of one of their possible types: 'D', 'F', 'X', and 
'S'. Names must not contain newline characters (the tree will be rejected if they
do).
</p>

<h3>Directories</h3>

<p>
'D' nodes correspond to directories, and their line format is:
</p>

<pre>"D", space, mtime, space, full path name, newline</pre>

<p>
So, top level directories, for example, would have a "full path name" 
that matches the regular expression <b>^/[^/\n]+$</b>.
</p>

<h3>Files</h3>

<p>
'F' and 'X' nodes correspond to files and executable files, respectively, and
their line formats are:
</p>

<pre>"F", space, hash, space, mtime, space, size, space, file name, newline
"X", space, hash, space, mtime, space, size, space, file name, newline</pre>

<p>
As opposed to directories, no full path names are given. Hence, file 
names match <b>^[^/\n]+$</b> . The hash is the 40-byte hexadecimal representation of
the SHA-1 sum of the contents of the respective file. Hexadecimal digits a
through f are used (rather than A through F).
</p>

<h3>Symlinks</h3>

<p>
'S' nodes correspond to symbolic links, and their line format is:
</p>

<pre>"S", space, hash, size, space, symlink name, newline</pre>

<p>
The symlink name is given analogously to file names in 'F' and 'X' 
nodes.  The size of a symlink is the number of bytes in its target 
(name).  The hash sum, similarly to that of files, is the SHA-1 sum of 
the target (name) of the respective symlink.
</p>

<h3>Other files types</h3>

<p>
It is an error for a tree to contain other types of object (such as device files).
Such trees are rejected.
</p>

<h3>Ordering</h3>

<p>
These lines appear in the order of a depth-first search where siblings 
in the directory tree are ordered lexicographically by their name, i.e., 
they appear in the order that "LC_ALL=C sort" would produce.
</p>

<p>
Implementations have to abide by these rules by the letter because such 
a file is to be generated automatically and this process absolutely must 
generate the same file that the directory tree packager had computed.
</p>

</html>
