<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html lang="en">

<h2>Installation : Windows</h2>

<p>
Windows is not currently supported, but if you have some programming knowledge, please help out!
</p>

<p>Here's how to test it</p>

<ol>
 <li>Install <a href='http://code.google.com/p/msysgit/'>msysgit</a></li>
 <li>Run git-gui from the Start menu, and clone <b>git://repo.or.cz/zeroinstall.git</b></li>
 <li>Install python-2.5.2.msi from <a href='http://www.python.org'>python.org</a></li>
 <li>Install gtk-2.12.9-win32-2.exe from link on <a href='http://www.pygtk.org/downloads.html'>pygtk.org's download page</a></li>
 <li>Install PyGObject and PyGTK from the same page</li>
 <li>Install Windows binary of GnuPG from <a href='http://gnupg.org'>gnupg.og</a></li>
 <li>Install Windows binary of bzip2 from <a href='http://www.bzip.org/'>bzip.org</a>. Call it <b>bunzip2.exe</b> and put it in your %PATH.</li>
 <li>Go to <b>Start -> Control panel -> System -> Advanced -> Environment Variables</b>. Edit "Path". Append: <b>;c:\python25;c:\gnupg</b> (or wherever you installed Python and GnuPG)</li>
 <li>Use <b>Start -> Run -> cmd</b>. Make sure the <b>python</b> and <b>gpg</b> commands can be found</li>
</ol>

<p>
You can now cd to your cloned GIT repository and run 0launch (use <b>-vvc</b> for maximum logging). This will probably fail. See if you can make it work. Open issues:
</p>

<p><strong>2009-02-03: Update: there is a new "windows" branch which gets a bit further... ("git checkout windows")</strong></p>

<ul>
 <li>The InputBlocker in download.py doesn't work. You can replace the whole line with just <b>yield</b> as a work-around. This is inefficient, but works. [ in the windows branch ]</li>
 <li>It thinks gpg isn't in $PATH. Edit gpg.py to disable that check. Ideally, patch it to actually search the Windows %PATH% correctly. [ fixed on windows branch ]</li>
 <li>All downloads have \r codes inserted into them. Looks like subprocess.Popen in download.py is turning a binary file into a text file. How can that happen? [ fixed on windows branch ]</li>
 <li>/var/cache/0install.net isn't a good place for the system store on Windows. Where should it go?</li>
 <li>os.utime fails for some reason. Shouldn't be needed with recent Python versions anyway.</li>
 <li>Unpacking loses the X permission, causing the digest check to fail. Store it in some DOS attribute?</li>
</ul>

<p>
That's as far as we've got so far. Let us know how you get on. Good luck!
</p>

<quicklinks>
  <link href='injector-using.html' img='tango/go-next.png'>Continue to tutorial</link>
</quicklinks>

</html>
