<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<h2>Similar or related systems</h2>

<dl class='spaced'>
<dt>Java Web Start</dt>
<dd>
<p>
Sun have developed a similar system to Zero Install,
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart">Java Web Start</a>,
although this only works for Java applications.
</p>
</dd>

<dt>Konvalo</dt>
<dd>
<p>
Konvalo was a very similar idea to the old Zero Install filesystem, but
implemented using CODA rather than with a custom kernel module.</p>

<p>
One disadvantage of Konvalo was that you needed to run a public CODA server
to distribute software, whereas both Zero Install implementations only require
a web-server serving static pages.
</p>

<p>
The project did not attract support from the community and the author
abandoned the effort in April 2006, asking for links to it from this site
to be removed.
</p>
</dd>

<dt>Klik</dt>

<dd>
<p>
<a href='http://klik.atekon.de'>Klik</a> allows users to install software by clicking on 
links in web-pages (or even just by looking at a web page). Like Zero Install, it stores
each package in its own directory and sets environment variables to let it run.
There is a central server which sends shell scripts to clients; executing the
script causes the software to be downloaded and installed. This process is
started automatically by your web browser.
</p>

<p>
Klik is mainly focused on having a large selection of packages working now,
but pays little attention to security. Klik packages can be automatically
converted to Zero Install ones. See my <a
href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/node/290'>article about Zero Install
and Klik</a> for more details.
</p>

<p>Differences between Klik and Zero Install include:</p>

<ul>
<li>The recipes Zero Install downloads are XML files, not shell scripts (this is similar
to the difference between tar and shar files).</li>

<li>Zero Install downloads are GPG signed.</li>

<li>Zero Install is decentralised: you need permission from the Klik
maintainers to distribute a Klik package. You don't need anyone's permission to
distribute with Zero Install.</li>

<li>Zero Install can check for updates automatically (by default once a month,
but configurable). Klik requires you to check for updates yourself.</li>

<li>Zero Install handles dynamic linking. This allows upgrading a library to
benefit multiple applications, and saves space and bandwidth. It also lets you
use a different version of a library if you want. Klik bundles all dependencies
into the package (Zero Install also
<a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/Zero2Bundle'>supports</a> this mode
of operation if desired).</li>

<li>Zero Install can <a href='sharing.html'>share downloads</a> between users
safely, using cryptographic digests.</li>

<li>Zero Install supports compiling from source if you want, though not all
packages support this yet.</li>

<li>Zero Install lets you download older versions or programs or libraries.
Klik only provides a single version for download, although you can keep using
older versions once you've got them.</li>

<li>Zero Install is fully <acronym title='Open Source Software'>OSS</acronym>. Only the Klik client is.</li>

<li>Klik runs the 'intellipatch' script on downloads, which does a
search-and-replace for filename paths in binaries (simple text matching) and
changes them. This allows some programs which aren't built to be binary
relocatable to work. Zero Install doesn't support this, and requires binaries
to be relocatable in the first place.</li>

<li>Klik has many more packages available right now.</li>

<li>Zero Install is platform independent. Klik only runs on Linux.</li>
</ul>

</dd>

<dt>Maven</dt>

<dd>
<p>
<a href='http://maven.apache.org/'>Maven</a> is a build tool (like make or ant)
for Java programs. Although not an installation system, it is similar to
the injector in that each product has a <b>project.xml</b> file with a list of
dependencies. When building a product, maven downloads the specified version of
each dependency and stores it in a cache directory. Some differences between
maven 1.0 (I have not yet tested version 2.0) and the injector:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Only exact versions of dependencies are given. Maven cannot select the
best version from a set. In an installation system, this would lead to a lot
of extra downloads as programs used different library versions
unnecessarily. It also makes it harder to get security fixes.</li>
<li>
Dependencies are not fetched recursively. If A requires B, and B requires C,
then maven will not fetch C unless A requests it explicitly. 
</li>
<li>
The <b>project.xml</b> files are not signed, as they are not fetched by
maven. Only implementations are downloaded.
</li>
<li>
There is no digest of the downloads in the project file, so no security checks
are performed to confirm that the download is OK, and downloads cannot be
shared safely between users.
</li>
<li>
Only Java is supported (everything is added to CLASSPATH, nowhere else).
</li>
<li>
Dependencies are named using a simple two-layer system (e.g., axis/axis-jaxrpc).
Therefore, a central repository is required to avoid naming conflicts.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Note that you can use Zero Install in a maven-like way for compiling programs.
See <a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/node/289'>Easy GTK binary compatibility</a>
for an example of using Zero Install to compile a C program against an older version
of a library's header files to ensure greater compatibility.
</p>
</dd>

<dt>Autopackage</dt>
<dd>
<p>
Like Zero Install, <a href='http://autopackage.org/'>Autopackage</a> aims to
let users install software and to make software distribution decentralised.
The work done by the Autopackage developers to make packages relocatable is 
necessary for the Zero Install injector too. Some differences between this and
Zero Install:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A script inside each package installs the files, making sandboxing
difficult. It also <a href='http://www.kitenet.net/~joey/blog/entry/autopackage_designed_by_monkeys-2005-03-28-14-20.html'>makes conversion to other
packaging formats troublesome</a>.</li>
<li>Security features such as GPG signatures have not been implemented. Given
that packages are executable files, the design doesn't seem to allow this to be fixed.</li>
<li>Downloads cannot be safely shared between users.</li>
<li>No checking for updates or support for multiple versions.</li>
<li>Being closer to traditional installation, it's easier to package existing
applications with Autopackage.</li>
</ul>

<p>
Note that it is quite possible to list autopackages in a Zero Install feed, as
described in <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.autopackage.devel/5733/focus=5733'>this
post on the Autopackage mailing list</a>. In this case, no scripts are run during
installation (the package is treated as a normal archive), so not all packages will work,
but many do.
</p>

</dd>

<dt>EDOS</dt>

<dd>
<p>
The <a href='http://www.edos-project.org/xwiki/bin/Main/'>EDOS</a> (<i>Environment
for the development and Distribution of Open Source software</i>) project is a research
project looking at dependency management, QA, and efficient distribution of
large software systems.
</p>
</dd>

<dt>Nix</dt>

<dd>
<p>
<a href='http://nix.cs.uu.nl/'>Nix</a> is another "purely functional" package
manager. It is purely functional in the sense that each version of a package
has its own directory. As with Zero Install, "upgrading" creates a new
directory for the new version, rather than modifying the existing one. Unlike
Zero Install, however, whether a package is installed affects the behaviour of the
system. For example, running "firefox" when Firefox isn't installed produces an
error in Nix, whereas in Zero Install it will install Firefox first if missing
and then continue. In other words, installation has side-effects in Nix.
</p>

<p>
Additional feeds (e.g. for pre-built binaries) can be registered using
"nix-channel --add", which appears to work much like "0launch --feed", although
each channel can contain binaries for multiple packages.
The channel "MANIFEST" file doesn't appear to have a digital signature. Presumably this
will be added at some point.
</p>

<p>
Each version of a package has a digest (hash), which includes all build
dependencies (e.g. the version of the compiler used), just as it does in Zero
Install (for packages built using 0compile, at least).
</p>

<p>
An important difference between the two is that the Nix hash is a hash of the
<i>inputs</i> used to build the package, whereas the Zero Install hash is a
hash of the <i>resulting binary</i>.
Nix does this to support binaries that hard code
their own paths, since the final hash needs to be known at compile time.
For source (non-compiled)
packages, the Nix hash is a hash of the contents, as with Zero Install.
The Zero Install hash often happens to include the inputs, since it covers the
"build-environment.xml" file which 0compile places in each binary package. Zero
Install doesn't allow binaries to include hard-coded paths.
</p>

<p>Update: Nix is planning to use binary hashes everywhere in future (zeroing out
self-references for the purposes of calcuating the hashes). The same thing was proposed
a few years ago for Zero Install (the
<a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/882/focus=882'>relocation table</a>).
It relies on the cache directory being at a fixed location, whereas people often have Zero Install
set up to use their home directory, but it's basically a good idea.</p>

<p>
Another difference between Nix and Zero Install is that Nix treats configurations
as packages. Changing your configuration is like "upgrading" your configuration
package to a new version. Rolling back a change is like reverting to a previous
version. Zero Install doesn't generally handle configuration settings,
preferring to let the user use subversion (or similar) for that, but it's an interesting idea.
</p>

<p>
Building a Nix package involves creating a "Nix expression" in a (custom)
functional language. The expression fills the same role as a Zero Install source
feed: it says where to download the source, what its digest is, what the
build dependencies are, and how to build it.
</p>

<p>
While Zero Install is mainly targeted at adding additional packages to an existing
system, Nix aims to manage the whole system (although it installs cleanly alongside
your existing package manager). Nix packages have short names (like "perl") not
full URIs, and thus it appears to assume a centrally-controlled repository.
</p>

<p>
In Nix, mutually untrusting users cannot share packages. The manual says <q>A setuid
installation should only by used if the users in the Nix group are mutually
trusted, since any user in that group has the ability to change anything in the
Nix store</q>. Because the Nix hash is a hash of the inputs, it is not possible
for the system to verify that a package is valid (it would have to download the
sources and compile the program itself; Nix can share binaries in this case).
Because Zero Install hashes are always hashes of the package contents, it does
support <a href='sharing.html'>sharing</a>.
</p>

</dd>

</dl>

<p>
See the <a href='matrix.html'>matrix</a> for a comparison of Zero Install's features with
those of other installation systems.
</p>

<h2>Articles about Zero Install</h2>
<p>Here are some discussions about Zero Install I've found on the web (Google, emails, etc). Let me
know if you find any more!</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.linux.com/article.pl?sid=07/02/15/0724206">Zero Install: An executable critique of native package systems</a> linux.com review and interview</li>
<li><a href="http://www.osnews.com/story.php/16956/Decentralised-Installation-Systems/">Decentralised Installation Systems</a> essay on OSNews.com</li>
<li><a href="http://www.pro-linux.de/news/2005/8310.html">Neue Zero Install-Implementation</a> article on pro-linux.de (in German)</li>
<li><a href="ZeroInstall-Ottawa-2004.sxi">My slides from the 2004 Desktop Developers' Conference</a> (in Ottawa, Canada, July 19-20, 2004; these slides include the questions asked during the talk)</li>
<li><a href="http://diariored.com/blog/000753.php">Zero Install System: instalar programas se va a acabar</a> (in Spanish)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.golem.de/0404/30666.html">Zero Install: Software-Installation der Zukunft?</a> (in German)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.linuxfrench.net/article.php?id_article=1268">Zero Install : si t’installes, t’es un Zéro!</a> (in French)</li>
<li><a href="http://osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=6596">Introduction to the Zero Install System</a> (OSnews article and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=04/04/03/174249&amp;mode=nested&amp;tid=106&amp;tid=185">Zero Install: The Future of Linux on the Desktop?</a> (Slashdot article)</li>
<li><a href="http://freshmeat.net/articles/view/1049/">Zero Install and the Web of Software</a> (my freshmeat editorial and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=5394">Zero Install and the Web of Software</a> (OSnews article and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://slashdot.org/~Sanity/journal/47655">Package Management in the ultimate operating system</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ed.puddingbowl.org/archives/001198.html">Ed Heil's Weblog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.varlinux.org/vl/html/modules/newbb/viewtopic.php?topic_id=201&amp;forum=8">Blue Sky Platform discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=114652">Gentoo forums discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="http://freedesktop.org/pipermail/xdg/2004-March/003461.html">Using Zero Install for sandboxing</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
<a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Installation.html">Tim Berners-Lee's "Installation, Catalogs, and Caches"</a> (DRAFT version) mentions Zero Install, too! (though the comment about needing a constant connection is wrong)
</p>

</html>
