<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<h2>Similar systems</h2>

<dl class='spaced'>
<dt>Java Web Start</dt>
<dd>
It appears the Sun have developed a similar system to Zero Install,
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart">Java Web Start</a>,
although this only works for Java applications.
</dd>

<dt>Konvalo</dt>
<dd>
<a href="http://www.konvalo.org/">Konvalo</a> is a very similar idea
to Zero Install, implemented using CODA.
</dd>

<dt>Maven</dt>

<dd>
<a href='http://maven.apache.org/'>Maven</a> is a build tool (like make or ant)
for Java programs. Although not an installation system, it is similar to
the injector in that each product has a <b>project.xml</b> file with a list of
dependencies. When building a product, maven downloads the specified version of
each dependency and stores it in a cache directory. Some differences between
maven 1.0 (I have not yet tested version 2.0) and the injector:
<ul>
<li>Only exact versions of dependencies are given. Maven cannot select the
best version from a set. In an installation system, this would lead to a lot
of extra downloads as programs used different library versions
unnecessarily. It also makes it harder to get security fixes.</li>
<li>
Dependencies are not fetched recursively. If A requires B, and B requires C,
then maven will not fetch C unless A requests it explicitly. 
</li>
<li>
The <b>project.xml</b> files are not signed, as they are not fetched by
maven. Only implementations are downloaded.
</li>
<li>
There is no digest of the downloads in the project file, so no security checks
are performed to confirm that the download is OK, and downloads cannot be
shared safely between users.
</li>
<li>
Only Java is supported (everything is added to CLASSPATH, nowhere else).
</li>
<li>
Dependencies are named using a simple two-layer system (e.g., axis/axis-jaxrpc).
Therefore, a central repository is required to avoid naming conflicts.
</li>
</ul>
</dd>

<dt>Autopackage</dt>
<dd>
Like Zero Install, <a href='http://autopackage.org/'>Autopackage</a> aims to
let users install software and to make software distribution decentralised.
The work done by the Autopackage developers to make packages relocatable is 
necessary for the Zero Install injector too. Some differences between this and
Zero Install:
<ul>
<li>A script inside each package installs the files, making sandboxing
difficult. It also <a href='http://www.kitenet.net/~joey/blog/entry/autopackage_designed_by_monkeys-2005-03-28-14-20.html'>makes conversion to other
packaging formats troublesome</a>.</li>
<li>Security features such as GPG signatures have not been implemented. Given
that packages are executable files, the design doesn't seem to allow this to be fixed.</li>
<li>Downloads cannot be safely shared between users.</li>
<li>No checking for updates or support for multiple versions.</li>
<li>Being closer to traditional installation, it's easier to package existing
applications with Autopackage.</li>
</ul>
</dd>

</dl>

<p>
See the <a href='matrix.html'>matrix</a> for a comparison of Zero Install's features with
those of other installation systems.
</p>

<h2>Articles about Zero Install</h2>
<p>Here are some discussions about Zero Install I've found on the web (Google, emails, etc). Let me
know if you find any more!</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.pro-linux.de/news/2005/8310.html">Neue Zero Install-Implementation</a> article on pro-linux.de (in German)</li>
<li><a href="ZeroInstall-Ottawa-2004.sxi">My slides from the 2004 Desktop Developers' Conference</a> (in Ottawa, Canada, July 19-20, 2004; these slides include the questions asked during the talk)</li>
<li><a href="http://diariored.com/blog/000753.php">Zero Install System: instalar programas se va a acabar</a> (in Spanish)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.golem.de/0404/30666.html">Zero Install: Software-Installation der Zukunft?</a> (in German)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.linuxfrench.net/article.php?id_article=1268">Zero Install : si t’installes, t’es un Zéro!</a> (in French)</li>
<li><a href="http://osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=6596">Introduction to the Zero Install System</a> (OSnews article and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=04/04/03/174249&amp;mode=nested&amp;tid=106&amp;tid=185">Zero Install: The Future of Linux on the Desktop?</a> (Slashdot article)</li>
<li><a href="http://freshmeat.net/articles/view/1049/">Zero Install and the Web of Software</a> (my freshmeat editorial and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=5394">Zero Install and the Web of Software</a> (OSnews article and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://slashdot.org/~Sanity/journal/47655">Package Management in the ultimate operating system</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ed.puddingbowl.org/archives/001198.html">Ed Heil's Weblog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.varlinux.org/vl/html/modules/newbb/viewtopic.php?topic_id=201&amp;forum=8">Blue Sky Platform discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=114652">Gentoo forums discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="http://freedesktop.org/pipermail/xdg/2004-March/003461.html">Using Zero Install for sandboxing</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
<a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Installation.html">Tim Berners-Lee's "Installation, Catalogs, and Caches"</a> (DRAFT version) mentions Zero Install, too! (though the comment about needing a constant connection is wrong)
</p>

</html>
