<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html>

<div>
<h2>News</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Apr 2011</dt>
<dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3960'>0launch 0.54</a> and <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/4076'>0launch 1.0-rc1</a> released. New features include an improved cache explorer, better support for running Python programs, and simpler behaviour for the Compile button. There have also been several new releases of the Windows version, which now supports background updates, self-update, and the new command-line interface. Other new releases this month include <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3990'>0publish-gui 0.11</a>, <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/4004'>0release 0.13</a>, <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/4074'>0compile 0.24</a>. Finally, there's a new <a href='using-git.html'>guide for making translations</a>.</dd>
<dt>Mar 2011</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3888'>0launch 0.53 released</a> with fewer key confirmation boxes, support for Ruby gems and an important bug-fix for the &lt;command&gt; support. The <a href='http://0install.net/install-mac.html'>Mac OS X binary package</a> is much improved. <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3929'>0compile 0.23</a> has been released with support for compiling Java programs. <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3920'>Improved cache explorer</a> and <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3847'>feed search</a> features are under development.</dd>
<dt>Feb 2011</dt><dd>Updated <a href='roadmap.html'>the roadmap</a> to plan for a 1.0 release this summer. There's now an (experimental) <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3584/focus=3819'>binary package for Mac OS X</a>. New releases of <a href='0publish.html'>0publish</a>, <a href='0compile.html'>0compile</a> and <a href='0export.html'>0export</a> to support recent changes in 0launch and fix a few bugs.</dd>
<dt>Jan 2011</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3702'>0launch 0.52</a> released. There's a new "0install" command providing a cleaner command-line interface, support for literal values for environment variables, more friendly default behaviour for 0alias, support for recursive &lt;runner&gt;s and some cleanups to the Python API. The <a href='http://0install.de'>Windows version</a> now provides a GUI for managing the cache and support for the &lt;command&gt; element.</dd>
<dt>Dec 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3568'>0launch 0.51</a> released with the new command support. New releases of <a href='0test.html'>0test</a> and <a href='0publish.html'>0publish</a>.</dd>
<dt>Nov 2010</dt><dd>The new <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3566'>&lt;command&gt;</a> work has now been merged. This is intended to replace 'main', 'test' and similar attributes with a more flexible and generic system. It allows passing extra arguments to commands (including passing dependencies), having command-specific dependencies, and being able to specify an intepreter in a cross-platform way.</dd>
<dt>Oct 2010</dt><dd>A first binary of the <a href='http://0install.de/downloads/'>Windows version</a> has been released.</dd>
<dt>Sep 2010</dt><dd>Lots of discussion about laying an <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3478'>app store</a> interface on top of Zero Install.</dd>
<dt>Aug 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3472'>0launch 0.50 released</a>. The <a href='ebox.html'>EBox security demonstration</a> was launched, showing how to integrate Zero Install with sandboxing, allowing users to run software they don't trust fully in a restricted environment. See if you can break out of the sandbox!</dd>
<dt>Jul 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3403'>0launch 0.49 released</a>, with the new PackageKit support. There's a new <a href='http://repo.or.cz/w/zeroinstall.git/shortlog/refs/heads/ironpython'>IronPython branch</a>, using the .NET mainloop instead of GLib, which means fewer dependencies for Windows users. <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3419'>0export 0.2</a> released, including a new --net-install mode. And we have a lovely <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3398/focus=3418'>new logo</a> (shown top-left).</dd>
<dt>Jun 2010</dt><dd>The big news this month is the new support for <a href='http://www.packagekit.org/'>PackageKit</a> - if a Zero Install program depends on an uninstalled distribution package, Zero Install can use PackageKit to install it, using the distribution's native package manager. The new <a href='0test.html'>0test</a> now has HTML output to show the test results matrix as a colourful table.</dd>
<dt>May 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3267'>0launch 0.48</a> (and 0.47) released, with support for selecting downloads by language, support for native Slackware and FreeBSD packages as dependencies. Development of <a href='http://0install.de'>the .NET version</a> continues.</dd>
<dt>Apr 2010</dt><dd><a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3090'>0launch 0.46 released</a>, with the new SAT solver. Feeds for <a href='http://repo.roscidus.com/devel/pkg-config'>pkg-config</a> and <a href='http://repo.roscidus.com/devel/make'>make</a> are now available so they can be used as build dependencies with <a href='0compile.html'>0compile</a>. <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3126'>Distribution integration for Gentoo and FreeBSD Ports</a> has been added. An <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3109'>OpenOffice.org feed</a> is under development.</dd>
<dt>Mar 2010</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.45</a> released, with support for native Gentoo packages and distribution-specific package names, better support for alternative digest algorithms and better support for pathnames on Windows. A new <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/3082'>SAT solver</a> has been implemented, which can select the best set of versions in every situation. <a href='http://roscidus.com/0mirror/'>The feed mirror site</a> has been greatly upgraded, with per-user and per-site lists of feeds and rankings.</dd>
<dt>Feb 2010</dt><dd><a href='install-windows.html'>The Windows version</a> is coming along nicely - please help to test it! Also, <a href='0export.html'>0export 0.1</a> was released; this allows easy creation of bundles for off-line distribution or archiving.</dd>
<dt>Jan 2010</dt><dd><a href='injector.html'>0launch 0.44</a> released. Improvements include a progress display in console mode, support for GnuPG 2, canonicalisation of architectures and some minor bug-fixes.</dd>
</dl>

<p>For more information see the <a href='support.html'>mailing list archives</a> and the <a href='roadmap.html'>roadmap</a>.
</p>

</div>

</html>
