<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>Roadmap</h2>

<p>
This document explains what we've done and where we're going with future versions.
</p>

<p>
Despite its pre-1.0 version number, Zero Install is currently used by a large
number of people, as it is the preferred method of installation for <a
href='http://rox.sourceforge.net'>ROX</a>, and is generally quite robust.
</p>

<h3>File format stability</h3>

<p>
Although we have not reached the 1.0 release, the injector has a very good
record of backwards compatibility. In fact, you can run Edit with the XML
interface file used to demonstrate version 0.2 of the injector (released
2005-03-14) on the very latest (0.22) version of the injector. The only
incompatible change was between versions 0.1 and 0.2!  Of course, it doesn't
work the other way; interfaces designed to work with later versions of the
injector will use features not available on older versions.
</p>

<h3>Completed features</h3>

<p>
This is a quick overview of the major features added to the injector. See the
<a href='http://www.gnomefiles.org/version.php?soft_id=921'>release notes</a> for a much more detailed
list.
</p>

<dl>
<dt>Dependencies, graphical interface, user-set policies</dt>
<dd>Since 0.1</dd>

<dt>Updating over HTTP, GPG signatures</dt>
<dd>Since 0.2</dd>

<dt>Pass options to programs</dt>
<dd>Since 0.5</dd>

<dt>Create alias scripts</dt>
<dd>Since 0.7</dd>

<dt>Automatic public key fetching</dt>
<dd>Since 0.8</dd>

<dt>Allow symlinks</dt>
<dd>Since 0.10</dd>

<dt>RPM packages of the injector</dt>
<dd>Since 0.13</dd>

<dt>Local interfaces and adding additional remote feeds</dt>
<dd>Since 0.14</dd>

<dt>Support for architecture-dependant binaries</dt>
<dd>Since 0.15</dd>

<dt>Additional feeds in interfaces</dt>
<dd>Since 0.17</dd>

<dt>Support FTP downloads of archives, XML signatures and extracting from RPMs</dt>
<dd>Since 0.18</dd>

<dt>Icons for interfaces, graphical cache explorer, and 0publish command to help with creating interface files</dt>
<dd>Since 0.19</dd>

<dt>Recipes</dt>
<dd>Combine several archives to create a single version.
Since 0.20</dd>

<dt>Restrictions on suitable versions of dependencies</dt>
<dd>Since 0.20</dd>

<dt>Extracting from Debian packages</dt>
<dd>Since 0.20</dd>

<dt>Support for other secure hashes</dt>
<dd>Since 0.20</dd>

<dt>Support for extracting from Autopackage and zip archives</dt>
<dd>Since 0.21</dd>

<dt>Secure local copy (checking the digest)</dt>
<dd>Since 0.22</dd>

<dt>Compile a binary from source</dt>
<dd>If a binary doesn't exist for your platform, the injector should be able to compile one from source for
you. This should include downloading any necessary compilers, headers and build tools using Zero Install. The
resulting binary should come with an automatically-generated interface file, ready for publishing the binary
on the web. The archive should also include a provenance file listing the exact versions of dependencies used
to build it, allowing it to be recompiled in the same environment later.
Supported since version 0.23.
</dd>

<dt>More flexible version numbering</dt>
<dd>
The injector only supports a list of dot-separated integers. It would be useful to support some common
modifiers, e.g. "1.0-pre1", "2.0.0-rc3", "5-post2". Since 0.24.
</dd>

<dt>Extracting from Cabinet packages</dt>
<dd>Since 0.24</dd>

<dt>Extracting from .tar.lzma and .tar (uncompressed) archives</dt>
<dd>Since 0.25</dd>
</dl>

<h3>Features planned for 1.0</h3>

<dl>
<dt>Automatic secure sharing of downloads</dt>
<dd>Make a SetUID helper that uses <b>0store copy</b> to copy downloads to a central cache. This allows
downloads to be shared without the intervention of the system administrator, while still preventing a
malicious (or virus-infected) user from compromising other user accounts. Need to think about how things
get removed from the cache when no longer needed!</dd>

<dt>Mirrors for archives</dt>
<dd>If a download site is unavailable, switch to another mirror. Support sf.net mirror system, custom mirror
systems, coral cache, etc. May need to show sponsor logos during the download.</dd>

<dt>Automatic cache cleaning</dt>
<dd>
The injector can keep all versions of all libraries on disk at once. This is useful, but there should be a way
to clean out ones that aren't needed any more to free up disk space. Individual versions can be removed easily
enough via the cache explorer, but it should be more automatic, a bit like "apt-get autoclean" or deborphan.
</dd>

<dt>Native package manager integration</dt>
<dd>
If a Zero Install package requires a library, and the user already has a suitable version installed with another
system (APT, RPM, etc) then the injector should be able to use that version. This would save unnecessarily downloading
and storing a second copy of the library. The user should still have the option to get the library through Zero Install
if they want though (e.g., if they want to try a newer version). Should we check for the presence of files or packages,
though?
</dd>

<dt>Optional dependencies</dt>
<dd>
The interface file format only allows 'required' dependencies at present. It should also support the
'recommended' (optional and selected by default) and 'suggested' (optional and unselected by default)
relationships.
</dd>

<dt>Display release notes</dt>
<dd>
The injector tells you that a new version is available, but it doesn't say what changed! At the very least, it
should provide a link to the program's release notes on the web.
[ <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/1316/focus=1316'>Discussion</a> ]
</dd>
</dl>

<h3>Other possible features</h3>

<dl>
<dt>Mirrors for interfaces</dt>
<dd>More difficult than mirrors for archives, since a malicious mirror could do a replay attack (giving an
older, but correctly signed, release that is known to be insecure) and users who don't check the signing
keys may be more at risk.</dd>

<dt>Plug-ins</dt>
<dd>
It should be possible to add additional interfaces to a program's dependencies list. For example, you could add
the interface for a French dictionary to a word processor to let you spell-check French documents.
This would usually require some support from the application itself. A plug-in is a more general type of
optional dependency; one which isn't listed in the main interface file at all.
[ <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/1072/focus=1073'>Discussion</a> ]
</dd>

<dt>More meta-data</dt>
<dd>License terms (and warn about incompatible licenses?), mailing list address, where to send
bug reports, etc.</dd>

<dt>Bug reporting</dt>
<dd>Generate useful information for bug-reports, since we know exactly which version of each library
was being used. <a href='0compile.html'>0compile</a> already supports this if a build fails, but we could
do something similar when running programs, too.</dd>

<dt>Peer-to-peer downloads</dt>
<dd>The tricky bit about P2P is normally the free-text searching, but we already know the secure hash
of the manifest we want, and when we get it we have the hash of every file we need, so this should be easy!
The idea is that if someone on your local network has already downloaded a program, you can get it from them
automatically.
[ <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/1262/focus=1266'>Discussion</a> ]
</dd>

<dt>Binary patches</dt>
<dd>
We have the secure hash of the currently-cached versions, so we can check that they're unmodified. In that case,
we could just download a delta to the next version rather than getting everything again. 0publish should create
these deltas automatically. Rsync may also be an option for some sites.
[ <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/1214/focus=1214'>Discussion</a> ]
</dd>

<dt>Kiosk mode</dt>
<dd>The system administrator can restrict what software users can install using Zero Install (white-list interface
URIs or trusted public keys).</dd>

<dt>Third-party sign-off</dt>
<dd>A distribution can sign an upstream release ("Certified for use with SuSE 10.2", etc). Users can set a policy
to run only approved versions by default. Or, a third-party could provide additional input to the hints box
(the injector's GUI contains a built-in "Unreliable hints database", but a commercial organisation could offer
a real service).
</dd>

<dt>Sandboxing</dt>
<dd>
Provide better integration with sandboxing systems such as <a href='http://plash.beasts.org/'>Plash</a>. It should be
possible to trust keys only in a limited way, so that such software must run in a sandbox. Sandboxed software must still
be able to run other programs through Zero Install, adding them to the cache as needed in a secure fashion.
[ <a href='http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel/1285/focus=1285'>Discussion</a> ]
</dd>

</dl>

</html>
