<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html>

<h2 id='lists'>Mailing lists</h2>

<p>The project has a single mailing list, which can be used for sending
bug reports, patches, suggestions, questions, etc.
</p>

<p>
Note: You cannot post without subscribing, due to the large amount of spam we
were getting, but you can subscribe and then disable mail delivery if you
prefer to read the list via one of the web interfaces below rather than by
getting emails.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Read with news-reader: <a href="news://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel">news://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel</a></li>
  <li>Read via web interface: <a href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel">gmane</a>, 
		    <a href="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum_name=zero-install-devel">SourceForce</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/zero-install-devel">Subscribe to get emails</a></li>
</ul>

<p>If clicking on the news: link above directly doesn't work:</p>

<ol>
<li>Load <b>Pan</b> (or some other news-reader) and add <b>news.gmane.org</b> as a new server (<b>Edit-&gt;Edit News Servers</b>).</li>
<li>Type <b>zero-install</b> into the group search box (top left).</li>
<li>You can right click over the group and choose <b>Subscribe</b> from the
menu to make it easier to find it in future. Note that 'Subscribing' to a
news group just marks it as interesting to your news-reader. It is
different to subscribing to get emails.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id='bugs'>Bug tracker</h2>

<p><strong>2012-08-25 : Notice : </strong>We have just upgraded to the new sf.net project format, which has broken 0install's integrated bug-reporting feature. Bug reports sent from the software appear to be delivered, but they are not. A fix will be in 0install 1.11 - sorry!</p>

<p>Bugs can also be filed on the bug tracker. However, it's best to post
non-trivial bugs to the mailing list too, as more people will see them
there.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://sourceforge.net/p/zero-install/bugs/">View open bugs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sourceforge.net/p/zero-install/bugs/new/">Submit a new bug</a> (you'll need to log in or register)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id='IRC'>IRC</h2>

<p>We can (occasionally) be found on IRC on Freenode, in #0install.</p>

<h2 id='email'>Email</h2>

<p>
If possible, please send questions and comments to the mailing list, so that other people
see them and they appear in the searchable archives. It's also more likely that
you'll get a reply if more people see your question. Messages sent directly to
me will be forwarded to the mailing list first, unless you specifically ask me
not to do this.
</p>

<p>
However, reports of security problems or requests for interviews may be
<a href='http://sourceforge.net/users/tal197/'>sent by email</a>.
</p>

<h2 id='commercial'>Commercial support</h2>

<p>
If you require commercial support, you can either ask on the mailing list (see above) or email.
Please say what kind of support you need: do you want a new feature implemented, or help making your existing application available?
</p>

</html>
