<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<h2>Mailing lists</h2>

<p>The project has a single mailing list, which can be used for sending
bug reports, patches, suggestions, questions, etc. You can post without subscribing
if you want to read the list via one of the web interfaces below rather
than by getting emails.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Read with news-reader: <a href="news://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel">news://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel</a></li>
  <li>Read via web interface: <a href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.file-systems.zero-install.devel">gmane</a>, 
		    <a href="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=zero-install-devel">SourceForce</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/zero-install-devel">Subscribe to get emails</a></li>
</ul>

<div class='note' style='text-align: left'>
<h3>If clicking on the news: link above directly doesn't work</h3>

<ol>
<li>Load <b>Pan</b> (or some other news-reader) and add <b>news.gmane.org</b> as a new server (<b>Tools-&gt;News
Servers</b>).</li>
<li>Select <b>gmane</b> using the <b>Server</b> menu.</li>
<li>Type <b>zero-install</b> into the group search box (top left) and press
<b>Return</b> to find the group.</li>
<li>You can right click over the group and choose <b>Subscribe</b> from the
menu to make it easier to find them in future. Note that 'Subscribing' to a
news group just marks it as interesting to your news-reader. It is
different to subscribing to get emails.</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2>Bug tracker</h2>

<p>Bugs can also be filed on the bug tracker. However, it's best to post
non-trivial bugs to the mailing list too, as more people will see them
there.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=76468&amp;atid=547191">View open bugs</a></li>
<li><a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=add&amp;group_id=76468&amp;atid=547191">Submit a new bug</a></li>
</ul>

<h2>Common problems</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.desktop.rox.user/5780">DBus.error.Disconnected:
Disconnected before receiving a reply</a> (when using 0refresh; an old version of Zero Install was not fully uninstalled)</li>
</ul>

<h2>Email</h2>

<p>
Please do not contact me by email directly. This prevents other people from
seeing the question and its answer (on the lists or the searchable archives),
and means I have to answer the same questions over and over again. It's also
more likely that you'll get a reply if more people see your question. Messages
sent directly to me will most likely either be ignored or bounced to the
mailing list anyway.
</p>

</html>
