<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>Contents</h2>

<toc level='h2'/>

<h2>Zero Install tutorial part 3: Policy settings</h2>

<p>
To get back to the policy box (so you can change which versions of Edit and
ROX-Lib you want used), 0launch with the --gui option. If you created a shell alias,
you can run 0alias again as a shortcut:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0alias rox-edit</b>
</pre>

<p>
If, instead, you added it to the menu then choose <b>Zero Install -> Manage Applications</b>
from the <b>Applications</b> menu and click on the edit properties icon next to the application
(requires 0launch 0.34 or later):
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="457" height="364" src="screens/manage-apps.png" alt='0desktop --manage'/>
</p>

<p>
You can affect which versions are chosen by changing your policy. Three aspects
of your policy are shown in the Preferences window: <b>Network use</b>, <b>Freshness</b>
and <b>Help test new versions</b>:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="623" height="478" src="screens/preferences.png" alt='The Preferences dialog'/>
</p>

<p>
Click on <b>Help test new versions</b>, and
you may see the version numbers increase, as newer, less well tested, versions
are chosen.
However, you may not see any change at all, since there may not be new
testing versions available when you try this.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="569" height="364" src="inject.png"
     alt="Versions are selected according to the user's policy" />
</p>

<p>
To get Zero Install to notice that a new version is available, click on the <b>Refresh all now</b>
button (which fetches a fresh copy of each feed). You can also set the freshness
policy; it will automatically check for updates to feeds that haven't been
checked within the allowed time.
</p>

<p>
These are not the only policy settings. The rest are per-component, and are
accessed by double-clicking on a line in the list. This is described in the following sections.
</p>

<p>Note that all changes to your policy are saved as soon as you make them.
Clicking on <b>Cancel</b> will close the window without running the program,
but any changes made to the policy are not reversed.
</p>


<h3>Choosing different versions</h3>

<p>
The interface URI (<b>http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit</b>) is
used to get the default list of implementations. You can see the information
about an interface by double-clicking on it in the list of interfaces. For
example, double-clicking on <b>Edit</b> displays this dialog box:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="566" height="420" src="screens/edit-properties.png"
  	alt="Properties of the Edit interface" />
</p>

<p>
The list of feeds shows all the places where Zero Install looks for versions of Edit.
By default, there is just one feed, whose URL is simply Edit's URI; you can
view it in a web browser if you're interested:
<a href="http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit">Edit's default feed</a>. This is
an XML file with a GPG signature at the end. The downloaded feed files are stored
locally in <b>~/.cache/0install.net/interfaces</b>.
</p>

<p>
The Versions tab shows all the versions found in all of the feeds:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="557" height="321" src="screens/edit-versions.png"
  	alt="Versions of the Edit" />
</p>

<p>
</p>

<h3>Stability</h3>

<p>
The feed file also gives a stability rating for each implementation. The following
levels are allowed:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Stable</li>
<li>Testing</li>
<li>Developer</li>
<li>Buggy</li>
<li>Insecure</li>
</ul>

<p>
Stability ratings are kept independently of the implementations, and are expected to change over
time. When any new release is made, its stability is initially set to <b>Testing</b>. If you
have selected <b>Help test new versions</b> in the Preferences dialog box then you will then start using it.
Otherwise, you will continue with the previous stable release. After a while
(days, weeks or months, depending on the project) with no serious problems
found, the author will change the implementation's stability to <b>Stable</b> so that
everyone will use it.
</p>

<p>
If problems are found, it will instead be marked as <b>Buggy</b>, or <b>Insecure</b>. Neither
will be selected by default, but it is useful to see the reason (you might opt to
continue using a buggy version if it works for you, but should never use an insecure
one). <b>Developer</b> is like a more extreme version of <b>Testing</b>, where the program is
expected to have bugs.
</p>

<p>
You can use the <b>Preferred Stability</b> setting in the interface dialog to choose which
versions to use. You can also change the stability rating of any implementation by clicking on it
and choosing a new rating from the popup menu. User-set ratings are shown in capitals.
</p>

<p>
As you make changes to the policy and ratings, the order of the implementations in the list
will change. The version at the top is the one that will actually be used. In addition
to the ratings above, you can set the rating to <b>Preferred</b>. Such versions always come first,
unless they're not cached and you are in Off-line mode.
</p>

<p>
Note: If you want to use the second item on the list because the first is
buggy, for example, then it is better to mark the first version as buggy than to mark the
second as preferred. This is because when a new version is available, you will want that to
become the version at the top of the list, whereas a preferred version will always be first.
</p>

<h2>How to I uninstall things?</h2>

<p>
Click on the <b>Cache</b> button in the main window to get the cache
explorer. Select the versions you don't need anymore and click on <b>Delete</b>.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="812" height="334" src="injector-cache.png"
  	alt='Uninstalling programs'/>
</p>

<h2>List of Zero Install software</h2>

<p>
See the <a href='injector-feeds.html'>packages</a> page for a list of software currently available
through Zero Install. See the <a href='injector-packagers.html'>packaging guide</a> for instructions
on how to provide software yourself.
</p>
 
</html>
