<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html>

<h2>Making shortcuts</h2>

<p>
  Shortcuts provide an easy way to run a program without entering the full URI,
  just like a bookmark in a web-browser provides an easy way to return to a web
  page without entering the full URL. 
</p>

<p>
Different environments provide different ways to add shortcuts.
</p>

<toc level="h3"/>


<h3>GNOME</h3>

<p>
  Choose <b>Zero Install -> Add New Program</b> from the <b>Applications</b>
  menu.  Type in the URI, or drag it from the web-browser into the dialog box.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="335" height="259" src="tutorial/add-with-gnome.png" alt='Adding with GNOME'/>
</p>

<p>
  <b>Ubuntu users</b>: You need to open and then close the menu editor after
  adding a program before it will show up; see 
  <a href='https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/xdg-utils/+bug/191958'>Ubuntu
  bug #191958</a>. You can also run programs directly by choosing <b>Manage
  Programs</b> from the menu.
</p>


<h3>KDE</h3>

<p>
  Choose <b>Add Zero Install Program</b> from the <b>Utilities</b> menu. Type
  in the URI, or drag it from the web-browser into the dialog box.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="318" height="165" src="tutorial/add-with-kde.png" alt='Adding with KDE'/>
</p>


<h3>ROX</h3>

<p>
  Drag the link from your web-browser to the AddApp program, then drag the
  launcher from there to wherever you want it. 
  <a href='http://rox.sourceforge.net/desktop/AddApp'>AddApp</a>'s page has
  more details.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="546" height="184" src="tutorial/add-with-rox.png" alt='Adding with ROX'/>
</p>


<h3>Finder</h3>

<p>
  Copy the link from your web-browser to the AddApp program, then save the
  launcher from there to wherever you want it.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
  <img width="591" height="200" src="tutorial/add-with-finder.png" alt='Adding with Finder'/>
</p>


<h3>Shell</h3>

<p>
  The <b>0alias</b> command can be used to create little shell scripts to start
  programs easily:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>0alias rox-edit http://rox.sourceforge.net/2005/interfaces/Edit</b>
</pre>

<p>
  The command puts the script in the first writable directory in your $PATH.
  You can now run Edit like this:
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>rox-edit</b>
</pre>

<p>
  Note: aliases are being replaced by <a href='user-guide-apps.html'>apps</a>. Since 0install 1.14, trying to create an alias will create an app instead.
</p>

<quicklinks>
  <link href='user-guide-first-launch.html' img='tango/go-prev.png'>Go back</link>
  <link href='user-guide-apps.html' img='tango/go-next.png'>Continue</link>
</quicklinks>
 
</html>
