<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html>

<h2>First Launch</h2>
<p>
  When launching a feed for the first time, 0install will download the
  necessary files for you and store them in <a href='user-guide-cache.html'>the cache</a>.
  Next time, 0install will use these stored files, so you don't need to download the
  program again. From time to time 0install will check for updates and offer to
  download them. For example:
</p>

<pre>
  $ 0launch http://www.nongnu.org/clanbomber/zeroinstall/ClanBomber.xml
</pre>

<table class='howitworks'>
 <tr><th colspan='2'>1. Confirm the keys</th></tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/confirm-key.png' alt='' width='400' height='323'/></td>
  <td>
      <p>Zero Install downloads information about the program from the given address.</p>
      <p>It checks that the information is signed using a GPG key you trust, confirming first if not.
      Even if you don't know about this key yet, it may provide a hint if it's in our database.</p>
    <p>[ Note: newer versions skip this confirmation for keys in the database. You can set
      it to confirm all keys in the Preferences dialog if you prefer the old behaviour. ]</p>
  </td>
 </tr>

 <tr><th colspan='2'>2. Download the files</th></tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/find-libraries.png' alt='' width='400' height='264'/></td>
  <td>
  <p>The downloaded file says that <b>ClanBomber</b> requires various libraries (SDL, libpng, etc).
Each library is identified by a web address (URL) in the same way that the main <b>ClanBomber</b> program was.
Zero Install downloads information about them in the same way. Since they may
be written by different people and be on different sites, you may be asked to confirm more keys. The window
displays a dialog box showing the program and all required libraries. Click <b>Download</b>.</p>
  </td>
 </tr>

 <tr><th colspan='2'>3. Wait for the download to finish</th></tr>
 <tr>
  <td class='image'><img src='screens/download-foo.png' alt='' width='400' height='349'/></td>
  <td>
  <p>Zero Install now downloads all the required archives (supported formats include tar.gz, tar.bz2, zip, 
rpm and deb). It unpacks each one into its own directory and
checks its contents against the <i>cryptographic digest</i>
given in the (signed) feed file. If the archive has been changed since the feed was signed,
the download will be rejected. If the archive hasn't been tampered with, it is stored in a cache directory
(see <a href='sharing.html'>sharing</a> for more information) in its own
subdirectory, named after the digest. This ensures that no two downloads can
conflict with each other.
  </p>
  </td>
 </tr>
</table>

<quicklinks>
  <link href='user-guide-intro.html' img='tango/go-prev.png'>Go back</link>
  <link href='user-guide-shortcuts.html' img='tango/go-next.png'>Continue</link>
</quicklinks>
 
</html>
